<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Venus in the cloister, Or The nun in her smock. In curious dialogues, addressed to the Lady Abbess of Loves Paradice, / by the Abbot Du Prat. ; Done out of French.</title>
            <title>Venus dans le cloitre ou La religieuse en chemise. English</title>
            <author>Barrin, Jean, ca. 1640-1718.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1683</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 170 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 87 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2014-11">2014-11 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A78196</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing B920B</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R174889</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">45097525</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">ocm 45097525</idno>
            <idno type="VID">171144</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online text creation partnership.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A78196)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 171144)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 2561:9)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>Venus in the cloister, Or The nun in her smock. In curious dialogues, addressed to the Lady Abbess of Loves Paradice, / by the Abbot Du Prat. ; Done out of French.</title>
                  <title>Venus dans le cloitre ou La religieuse en chemise. English</title>
                  <author>Barrin, Jean, ca. 1640-1718.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[6], 161 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed for H. Rodes, next dore to the Bear Tavern near Bride-Lane in Fleet-Street,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London, :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1683.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Translation of: Venus dans le cloitre ou La religieuse en chemise.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in the Bodleian Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Catholic Church --  Controversial literature.</term>
               <term>Anti-Catholicism.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2012-11</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-11</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-02</date>
            <label>Olivia Bottum</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-02</date>
            <label>Olivia Bottum</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2014-03</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:171144:1"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:171144:1"/>
            <p>
               <hi>VEN<g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>S</hi> in the Cloiſter, OR THE NUN in her Smock.</p>
            <p>In Curious DIALOGUES, ADDRESSED To the Lady Abbeſs of <hi>Loves Paradice,</hi> By the Abbot <hi>Du Prat.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Done out of French.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>LONDON,</hi> Printed for <hi>H. Rodes,</hi> next Dore to the Bear Tavern near <hi>Bride-Lane</hi> in <hi>Fleet-Street,</hi> 1683.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="dedication">
            <pb facs="tcp:171144:2" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:171144:2"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:171144:3"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:171144:3"/>
            <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
               <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
            </gap>
            <pb facs="tcp:171144:4"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:171144:4"/>
            <head>TO MADAM <hi>D. L. R.</hi> Moſt Worthy Abbeſs of <hi>Loves Paradice.</hi>
            </head>
            <opener>
               <salute>MADAM,</salute>
            </opener>
            <p>AS it would be a difficult matter for me not to comply with all your de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſires, I did not at all pauſe upon the Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>queſts I received from your Ladyſhip, for the reducing as ſoon as poſſible into wri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting, the ſecret Entertainments wherein your Society had ſo great a ſhare. I engaged my ſelf too ſolemnly in this Gallant Enterprize, for to decline now the going through with it, or to excuſe my proſecuting this Work, upon the difficulty there is to give to the <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>oice and Action that <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ivacity they were animated with. I know not if I ſhall have fully performed my Duty, and ſatis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fied
<pb facs="tcp:171144:5"/>your expectations, the exerciſe of two or three mornings will diſcover to you the Reſemblance or Imperfection of this Draught; and will let you know, that if I have not a great deal of Eloquence, I have at leaſt memory enough, faithfully to relate the greateſt part of things past. I have ſo propoſed to my ſelf your ſatisfaction in this <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ndertaking, that I have indifferent<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly paſſed over all the reaſons which ſeem to diſſwade me from it; the fear only of it's falling into any other hands than yours, has made me ſomewhat delay ſending it to you, and I my ſelf would have been the bearer, if my preſent affairs would have allowed me that ſatisfaction, rather than truſt to the hazard of a Poſt or of a Meſſenger a Packet of this conſequence. For in good earneſt, if the ſecret conferen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces ſhould happen to be made publick, it would Occaſion no ſmall ſcandal both to me and your Lady-ſhip; and if Actions which are not blamed, but becauſe they are not known, ſhould happen to become a new ſubject of Criticiſme, and furniſh arms to all thoſe who are willing to attack us; what a posture would our poor Nun be in, and with what Countenance can ſhe ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pear, if ſhe had the misfortune of being expoſed in her Smock to the ſight of all
<pb facs="tcp:171144:5"/>the curious? How much Scandal, Shame, and Diſorder would this Occaſion! All theſe conſiderations are ſtrong, but you will be O<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>beyed, &amp; you have termed ſure &amp; ſolid reaſons by the name of light and timerous Reflections.</p>
            <p>Let what will happen, I waſh my hands of all conſequences; &amp; to lay aſide this ſerious hu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mour, I may tell your Ladyſhip, that Siſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter <hi>Agnes</hi> has nothing to fear, though her ill Deſtiny ſhould concern it ſelf in the ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nagement of this buſineſs; for the Draught I have made of her in my Wri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tings, has repreſented her in a very exact obſervation of all her Vows; for indeed, to begin with Poverty; can one be in a great<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter diſengagement from the bleſſing of this World, than to ſtrip and deprive our ſelves of them, even to ones very Shift? Can we in our words or our actions ſhew the Beauty of Nature with more Luſtre, than by propoſing to ones ſelf for Rule, Nature altogether pure? in ſhort, if one had a mind to make trial of her Obedience without exception, ſhe would be found to have as much Docility as any one of your Novices.</p>
            <p>Thus you ſee Madam, you have a long Letter to a ſmall Work, and a great door to a little Houſe, but no matter: I choſe rather to ſin againſt the Rules, than to curb and conſtrain my ſelf in my writing
<pb facs="tcp:171144:6"/>to your Ladyſhip. Impart to your and my moſt intimate Friend, what you think fitting they ſhould know of this matter, and believe me to be without reſerve.</p>
            <closer>
               <salute>MADAM,</salute> 
               <signed>
                  <hi>Your Ladyſhips moſt Obedient, and moſt Affectionate Servant, The Abbot</hi> du Prat.</signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div n="1" type="dialogue">
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:171144:6"/>
            <head>
               <hi>Venus</hi> in the <hi>Cloister,</hi> OR THE <hi>Nun</hi> in Her <hi>Smock.</hi>
            </head>
            <head type="sub">Firſt <hi>Dialogue.</hi>
            </head>
            <stage>Siſter <hi>Agnes,</hi> Siſter <hi>Angelica.</hi>
            </stage>
            <sp>
               <speaker>AGnes.</speaker>
               <p>Ah Lord, Ah Lord! Siſter <hi>Angelica,</hi> pray come not in my Room, I am not viſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble at preſent: muſt you needs ſurprize People thus in this condi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion? I thought I had made the Door faſt.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Angelica.</speaker>
               <p>Well, well, hiſt, hiſt, why are you thus Alaram'd? a great hurt indeed, to have found
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:171144:7"/>thee changing thy Smock, or do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing ſomething better; Intimate Friends ought not in any wiſe to con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceal themſelves from one another. Sit thee down upon thy Bed in the ſame poſture thou waſt in: Ile go ſhut the Door.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Agnes.</speaker>
               <p>I aſſure you my dear Siſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter, that I ſhould have dyed for ſhame, if any other than you had ſurprized me in this pickle; but I am certain you have a great deal of af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fection for me; wherefore I have no reaſon to fear any thing from you whatſoever you may have ſeen.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Ang.</speaker>
               <p>Thou haſt reaſon my poor Chucky, to ſay what thou doſt; and though I ſhould not have for thee all the tenderneſs that a heart is capable of, nevertheleſs thy mind ought to be at reſt as to that. I have been now a <hi>Nun</hi> theſe <hi>Seven</hi> years, and I came into the Cloy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſter at <hi>Thirteen:</hi> and I may ſay, that <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> not yet by my ill conduct, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> any ones enmity; having
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:171144:7"/>always had detraction in abhor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rence, and doing nothing more to my hearts content, than when I render ſervice to any of the So<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciety. This courſe of Life has pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cur'd me the affection of the moſt part; much above all, has aſſur'd me of that of our <hi>Abbeſs,</hi> which is of no ſmall uſe to me upon occa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Agn.</speaker>
               <p>I know it, and have been often amaz'd, how you could ſo manage thoſe who are of a contra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry Party: It is undoubtedly requi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſite to be as well ſtock'd with wit and learning, as you are to manage ſuch like Perſons. For my part, I have never been able to Bridle my ſelf in my affections, nor endeavour to engage thoſe to be my Friends, who are naturally indifferent to me; It is the imperfection of my Geni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>us which is an Enemy of Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtraint, and will in all things act freely.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Ang.</speaker>
               <p>The truth is, that it is very
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:171144:8"/>
                  <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                     <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <pb n="3" facs="tcp:171144:8"/>
                  <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                     <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <pb n="4" facs="tcp:171144:9"/>ſweet and delightful to ſuffer owns ſelf to be led and conducted by that pure and innocent Nature, in only following the inclinations it gives us. But Honour and Ambition which are come to diſturb the re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe of Cloyſters, oblig'd thoſe who are engag'd in e'm, to divide themſelves, and to do often out of prudence, what they cannot do out of inclination.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Agn.</speaker>
               <p>That is to ſay, an infinite Number who think themſelves Miſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>treſſes of your heart, do only poſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeſs the painting of it, and that all your proteſtations aſſure 'em of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten of a bleſſing which they do not really enjoy, I muſt own that I ſhould very much ſuſpect my being of that number, and that I am a Vic<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>time of your Policy.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Ang.</speaker>
               <p>Ah my Dear! Thou doſt me an injury, diſſimulation has no ſhare in ſuch ſtrong friendſhip as ours! I am wholly thine, and though Nature had produced me
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:171144:9"/>from the ſame blood, it could not have given me ſentiments more tender than theſe I feel. Allow me to Embrace thee, that our hearts may ſpeak to one another in the midſt of our Kiſſes.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Agn.</speaker>
               <p>Ah God! how thou graſp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eſt me in thy Arms, thou little thinkeſt I am naked in my Smock! Ah! thou haſt ſet me all on a Fire.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Ang.</speaker>
               <p>Ah! how finely doth that Vermilion wherewith thou art at preſent animated, Augment the Luſtre of thy Beauty? Ah! How Amiable does that Brightneſs ren<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der thee which now ſparkles in thy eyes? No, no, my pretty Rogue, I will impart to thee my moſt ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cret acquiſitions, and give thee a perfect <hi>Idea</hi> of the Conduct of a Prudent <hi>Nun;</hi> I do not ſpeak of that Auſterity and Scrupulous wiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom, which is only nouriſh'd by faſtings, and only coverd with Hair Cloth; there is another Prudence leſs ſavage, which all underſtand<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:171144:10"/>perſons make profeſſion of fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowing, and which has no ſmall affinity to thy Amorous Nature.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Agn.</speaker>
               <p>I of an Amorous Nature, my Phiſiognomy muſt certainly be very deceitful, or elſe you are not perfectly well acquainted with the Rules of that Science, there is no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing which touches me leſs than this Paſſion, and for theſe three years that I have been a <hi>Nun,</hi> it has not given me the leaſt diſtur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bance.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Ang.</speaker>
               <p>That I very much doubt, and am of Opinion, if thou wouldſt ſpeak with more ſincerity, thou wouldſt own that I have ſaid no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing but what is true. How a Maiden of <hi>Sixteen,</hi> of ſo quick a Wit, and ſo handſome a Body as thine, ſhould be cold and inſenſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble: that I cannot perſwade my ſelf, all thy moſt careleſs actions have aſſur'd me of the contrary, <hi>And that I know not what,</hi> which I perceived through the Key-hole of
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:171144:10"/>the Door before I came into the Room, makes me know that thou art a diſſembler.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Agn.</speaker>
               <p>Ah Lord! Ah Lord! I am undone!</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Ang.</speaker>
               <p>Go thou ſilly Creature, what ſhouldſt thou apprehend from me? prethee tell me, haſt thou rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon to be afraid of a friend? I told thee this with no other deſign than to make thee my confident in ſeve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ral ſuch like caſes of my own: tru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly a fine buſineſs it is, but what the moſt ſcrupulous put in practiſe, and this is called in Cloiſtral terms, <hi>The Amuzement of the Young, and the Paſſion of the Old.</hi>
               </p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Agn.</speaker>
               <p>But pray what did you ſee then?</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Ang.</speaker>
               <p>Thou wearieſt me with thy fooling: doſt thou not know that Love baniſhes all fear, and that if we both mean to live in ſo perfect a correſpondence as I deſire we may, thou muſt hide nothing from me, and I muſt keep nothing
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:171144:11"/>ſecret from thee; Buſs me my pret<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty heart; conſidering thy perverſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs, a Diſcipline would be of good uſe to puniſh thee for the ſmall re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turns thou makeſt to the kindneſs one ſhews thee. Good God, how ſoft and plump art thou! Ah! thou art of a ſweet delicate ſhape? Let me—</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Agn.</speaker>
               <p>Ah! For Heaven's ſake let me alone! I cannot recollect my ſelf from this ſurprize: but in good earneſt, what did you ſee?</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Ang.</speaker>
               <p>Doſt thou not know thou little fool thou? what I might have ſeen? I ſaw thee in ſuch a Poſture and Action as if thou pleas'ſt I will ſerve thee in my ſelf; where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in my hand ſhall at preſent do thee the Office which thy own a while ago did ſo charitably render to a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nother part of thy Body; A very great crime indeed that I have diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cover'd, it is but what my Lady <hi>Abbeſs</hi> practices, as ſhe her ſelf ſays, in the moſt innocent diverſions; It
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:171144:11"/>is but what the Prioreſs does not re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ject; but what the miſtriſs of the novices calls <hi>The Exſtatical Intro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſſion?</hi> Thou couldſt not have be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lieved, that ſuch Holy Souls could have been capable of employing themſelves in ſuch profane Exerci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces? their mean and their outward behaviour have deceived thee, and that ſhew of Sanctity, with which they know ſo well how to deck themſelves upon occaſion, has made thee think they live in their Bodyes, as if they were compoſed of nothing but the Spirit. Ah my dear Child, I will inſtruct thee with a Number of things which thou art ignorant of, if thou would'ſt but have ſome confidence in me; and if thou letteſt me but know the diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſition of mind and conſcience thou art in at preſent: after which thou ſhalt be my Confeſſor, I will be thy Penitent; and I proteſt, that I will as freely unboſom to thee my heart, as if thou thy ſelf felteſt the pureſt motions of it.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <pb n="10" facs="tcp:171144:12"/>
               <speaker>Agn.</speaker>
               <p>After ſo many words, I do not think I ought to doubt of your ſincerity, wherefore I will not only tell you what you deſire to know of me, but I ſhall even take a ſenſible pleaſure in communica<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting to you my moſt ſecret thoughts and actions. It will be a general Confeſſion which I knew you have no deſign to prevail of, but the imparting whereof to you, ſhall only ſerve to unite us to one ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, with a more ſtrict and indiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoluble Bond.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Ang.</speaker>
               <p>It ſhall ſo, without doubt, My Dear, and thou wilt afterwards find, that there is nothing more de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lightful in this World, than to have a true Friend, who can be the de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſitary of our Secrets, of our Thoughts, and of our very Afflicti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons. Ah how Eaſing and Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fortable are thoſe diſcloſings of ones mind, in ſuch like Occaſions. Speak then: Prethee, My Dear, ſpeak. I will ſit down by thee upon thy
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:171144:12"/>Bed: 'Tis not neceſſary that thou dreſs thy ſelf, the Seaſon allows thee, to continue as thou art, Me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thinks! Thou art ſo much the more lovely, and the more thou aproach<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eſt the Eſtate wherein Nature brought thee into the World, the more Charms and Beauty doſt thou appear with. Hug me, My Dear <hi>Agnes,</hi> before thou beginneſt, and confirm by thy kiſſes the mutual Proteſtations We have interchang<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed of loving one another Eternal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly. Ah! how Pure and Innocent are theſe Kiſſes! Ah how full of Tenderneſs and Sweetneſs! Ah how they tickle me with Delight! Hold a little my Pretty Heart, I am all of a Flame, theſe Carreſſes have brought me into a Panting Condition; Ah God! How pow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>erful is Love; and what will be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>come of Me, if meer Kiſſes Ani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mate and Tranſport Me to ſuch a Pitch?</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Agn.</speaker>
               <p>It is indeed a very diffi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cult
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:171144:13"/>matter to contain ones Self within the bounds of ones Duty; when We in the leaſt ſlacken the Reines to that Paſſion; Would you believe it <hi>Angelica?</hi> Theſe little wantonings, which in the bottom are nothing, have had a wonder<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful effect upon me? Ah, Ah, Ah, let Me breath a little: Methinks my heart is too much pent up at preſent: Ah! theſe ſighs give me eaſe. I begin to have for you a new Affection, and more Strong and Tender than before: I know not from whence this proceeds; for can meer Kiſſes cauſe ſo much diſorder in a Soul? The truth is, you are very dextrous in your Car<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reſſes, and all your wayes are ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>traordinary engaging; for you have ſo won upon me, that I am more yours than I am my own; Beſides I am afraid, that in the Exceſs of the ſatisfaction which I have en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>joyed; there may have been ſome ſuch things as may give me occa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:171144:13"/>to reflect upon my conſcience, which I ſhould be very ſorry for; for when I am to ſpeak to my Confeſſour upon thoſe ſort of Mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters, I dye for ſhame, and know not where to begin. Ah Lord! How weak are We poor ſilly Crea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures, &amp; how vain are our efforts, for the ſurmounting the leaſt Sallyes, and the leaſt Attacks of a corrup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted Nature.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Ang.</speaker>
               <p>This is what I watcht for, I know thou haſt ever been ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing ſcrupulous upon ſeveral Sub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jects, and that a certain tenderneſs of Conſcience has given thee no ſmall trouble. This it is to fall into the Hands of a Curs'd and Ig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>norant Directour: For my part, I will tell thee that I have been taught by a Learned Man, with what air I am to comport my ſelf, for the living happy all my life long; yet without doing any thing that might diſtaſt and ſcandalize the ſight of a regular Society, or
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:171144:14"/>that was directly contrary to the Commands of God.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Agn.</speaker>
               <p>Oblige me Siſter <hi>Angelica,</hi> by giving me a perfect Idea of that happy Conduct; believe that I am entirely diſpoſed to hear you, and to ſuffer my ſelf to be perſwaded by your diſcourſes, when I am not able to deſtroy them by ſuch as are more ſtronger, and more pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vailing. The promiſe I have given you of diſcloſing my ſelf wholly to you, ſhall by theſe means be but the better obſerved, becauſe that inſenſibly in my anſwers which ſhall partake in our enter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tainment, you will obſerve what Method has been taken with me, and upon what foot I am fetled, and you will judge by the ſincere Confeſſion I ſhall make to you of all things, of the good or ill courſe I ſhall Steer.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Ang.</speaker>
               <p>Dear Child, thou wilt be ſurpriz'd perhaps at the Leſſons I am going to give thee, and thou
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:171144:14"/>wilt be amazed to hear a Maiden between <hi>Nineteen</hi> and <hi>Twenty</hi> years of Age, pretend to Dogmatize and Learning; and to ſee her Pry in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to the moſt hidden ſecrets of Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligious Policy. Do not my Dear, fancy that a Spirit of Vain Glory animates my Words; no, I know I was even leſs knowing than thou at thy age, and that all I have Learned, has ſucceeded to an ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tream Ignorance. But I muſt like<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe own to thee, that I ought to be accus'd of ſtupidity, if the Cares and Pains ſeveral Great Men have taken to form me, and ren<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der me perfect, had not been fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowed with any fruit: and if the Underſtanding they have given me of ſeveral Tongues, had not made me make ſome Progreſs by the Reading of good Books.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Agn.</speaker>
               <p>My dear <hi>Angelica,</hi> begin your Inſtructions I beſeech you: I Languiſh under the impatience I am in of hearing your Reaſonings:
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:171144:15"/>you never had a Schollar more at<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tentive, than I ſhall be to all your Diſcourſes.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Ang.</speaker>
               <p>As we are not born of a ſex to make Laws, we ought to obey thoſe we have found, and follow as known Truths, many things which of themſelves do on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly paſs with others for Opinions. I pretend, my dear Child, to con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>firm thee truly in the Sentiments thou haſt, that there is one Juſt and Merciful, who de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mands our homages, and who with the ſame mouth he forbids us what is Evil, Commands us the practiſe of what is Good. But as all do not agree what ought to be called Good or Evil; and that an infinite number of actions for which we are made to have a horrour, are re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceived and approved of by our Neighbours; I will tell thee in few words, what a Reverend Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther <hi>Jeſuite,</hi> who has a peculiar af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fection for me, told me at the time he
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:171144:15"/>endeavoured to open &amp; enlighten my evil mind and underſtanding, and to render e'm capable of the preſent Speculations.</p>
               <p>As all your happyneſs, my dear <hi>Angelica</hi> (ſo ſpoke he to me) de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pends on the perfect knowledg of the Religious Eſtate you have Em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>braced, I am willing to give you a natural account thereof, and at the ſame time furniſh you with the means of living, in your ſolitude, without any diſquiet or trouble which proceed from ſuch engage<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments. Now to go on methodi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cally in the Inſtructions I am to give you, you muſt remark, that Religion (I underſtand by that word, all the Monaſtical Orders) is compoſed of two Bodyes; where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of, the one is partly Celeſtial and Supernatural, and the other Ter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reſtrial and Corruptible, which is but an invention of Man; the one is Political, and the other Myſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cal by Relation to <hi>Jeſus Chriſt,</hi>
                  <pb n="18" facs="tcp:171144:16"/>who is the only head of the true Church. The one is permanent, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe it conſiſts in the Word of God, which is Immutable and E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ternal; and the other is ſubject to an infinite number of changes, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe it depends on that of Man, which is finite and fallible. This being ſuppoſed, thoſe two Bodyes are to be ſeparated, and a juſt di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtinction of them is to be made, that we may know what we are obliged to. But it is no ſmall dif<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ficulty to ſolve them well, the Po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>litical as the weakeſt part, has ſo uni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted it ſelf to the other, which is the ſtrongeſt, that all is almoſt at preſent confounded, and the voice of man confuſed with that of God. From this diſorder is it that do a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſe the illuſions, ſcruples, wracks, torments and groanings of Conſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence, which often bring a poor Soul into deſpair; and thence it is, that this yoak, which ought to be light and eaſie to bear, is become
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:171144:16"/>by the impoſition of men, heavy, painful, and inſupportable to ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny.</p>
               <p>Amongſt ſuch thick Clouds of darkneſs, and ſo viſible an altera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of all things, we muſt whol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly and ſolely apply our ſelves to the Body of the Tree, without troubling our ſelves to embrace it's ſprouts or it's branches. We muſt content our ſelves with O<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>beying the Precepts of the Sove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>raign Legislator, and hold for Certain, that all the Works of Su<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pererogation, to which the Voice of men would engage us, ought not to give us a moments diſquiet. We muſt in Obeying that God who Commands us, conſider if his Will is written with his own finger, if it proceeds from the mouth of His Son, or if it only departs from that of the People. So as Siſter <hi>An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gelica,</hi> may without ſcruple, light<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>en her chains, embeliſh her ſolita<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry way of Life, and by giving a
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:171144:17"/>chearful Air to all her Actions, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>come tame, grow familiar, and be acquainted with the World: ſhe may, continued he, diſpence her ſelf, as far as prudence will allow of, from the Execution and perfor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mance of all that hodge podge of vows and Promiſes, which ſhe has indiſcreetly made before men: and may again re-enter into the ſame Rights ſhe ſtood poſſeſs'd of before her engagement, following only theſe firſt Obligations.</p>
               <p>This is, purſued he, for what re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gards the inward Peace; Now as for the outward, you cannot with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out ſinning againſt prudence, diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pence your ſelf from ſeemingly af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fording a Complyance to the Laws, Cuſtomes &amp; Manners, which you ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jected your ſelf to, at your entrance into the Cloiſter. You muſt alſo ſeem zealous and fervent in the moſt painful Excrciſes, if any inte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reſt of Glory or of Honour de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pends on thoſe Occupations. You
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:171144:17"/>may deck your Chamber with ſack<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cloth and hair Shirts, and by that devout furniture merit as much as ſhe, who indiſcreetly ſhall go laſh and mortifie her Body.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Agn.</speaker>
               <p>Ah! how rejoyced am I to hear thee; the extream delight I took in thy diſcourſe has hinde<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red me from giving thee any inter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ruption, and that freedom of Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcience which thou beginneſt to a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ford me, by thy diſcourſe, unloads me almoſt of an infinite number of troubles wherewith I was torment<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed. But proceed I beſeech thee, and tell me what was the deſign of Policy, in the eſtabliſhment of ſo many Orders, whoſe Rules and Conſtitutions are ſo rigorous?</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Ang.</speaker>
               <p>We may conſider in the foundation of all Monaſteries, two workmen who hath laboured there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in, namely the Founder and Policy. The Intention of the former has of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten been Pure, Holy, and far from all the deſigns of the other. And
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:171144:18"/>without having any other proſpect than the Salvation of Souls, he has propoſed rules and ways of Living, which he thought neceſſary, or at leaſt uſeful, to his Spiritual advance<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, and to that of his Neighbour. By this means have Deſarts been populated and Cloiſters built; the Zeal of one Perſon alone enflamed ſeveral with the like, and their Prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cipal Occupation being to ſing con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinually the Praiſes of the true God, they draw by thoſe Pious exerciſes whole companies, who united them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves to them, and made but one Body. I ſpeak in this of what paſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed in the Fervency of the firſt A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ges. Now as for the reſt, we muſt take another Byaſs in our Reaſon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ings, and not imagine that this pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitive Innocence, and this fine Cha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>racter of Devotion did long pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerve it ſelf, and that it has been derived to &amp; inherited by thoſe we ſee at preſent.</p>
               <p>Policy, which can bear with nothing
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:171144:18"/>faulty in a State, ſeeing the en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>creaſe of theſe recluſed people, their diſorder and extravagancy, was obliged to Provide againſt fur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther miſchief, thereupon baniſhed ſeveral, retrenched the Conſtituti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons of others, which ſhe did not think neceſſary for the publick In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tereſt. It would willingly have got intirely rid of theſe Blood-ſuck<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ers, who in an horrible Idleneſs and Lazineſs nouriſhed themſelves with the labour of the poor people. But this Buckler of Religion where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>with they covered themſelves, and the Spirit of the vulgar People, which they had already decoyed and in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fatuated, have made her to go a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nother way to work, that ſo ſuch ſorts of Companies or Societies might not be entirely uſeleſs to the Common-Wealth.</p>
               <p>Thus Policy has looked upon all thoſe Houſes as Common places where it might diſcharge it ſelf of theſe following ſuperfluities: It
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:171144:19"/>makes uſe of them for the Eaſe of Families, which the great number of Children would render poor and indigent, if they had not places to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tire to: And that their retreat might be without hopes of Return, it has invented Vows, by which it pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tends to bind us and wed us indiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolvably to the ſtate it has made us embrace: It makes us renounce likewiſe the Rights which nature has given us, and ſeparates us ſo from the world, that we no longer make a part thereof. Thou conceiveſt all this well enough?</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Agn.</speaker>
               <p>Yes I do: but from whence comes it, that this curſed Policy, which of free people renders us ſlaves, approves more of thoſe rules which have nothing but what's Auſtere and Rigorous, than of thoſe that are leſs ſevere and painful?</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Ang.</speaker>
               <p>Why this is the Reaſon. It conſiders all Religious Orders, as <hi>Fryers, Nuns,</hi> and the Reſt, as members retrenched from its Body,
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:171144:19"/>and as parts ſeparated, whoſe life does not leane to it particularly for any thing beneficial, but much ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther damageable to the publick. And as it would be an action, that would appear inhumane, to take 'em away openly, it makes uſe of Stratagems, and under pretext of Devotion, it engages thoſe poor Vic<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tims (as it were) to cut their own throats, and to load themſelves with ſo many faſts, penances and mortifications, that at length theſe In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nocents fall under 'em, &amp; make way by their death for others, who are to be as miſerable, if they have not more underſtanding. After this manner does a Father often become the Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ecutioner of his own children, and without thinking of it, Sacrifices them to Policies, when he meant to make them an Offering to God.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Agn.</speaker>
               <p>Ah the piteous effect of a deteſtable Government! Thou giveſt me life, my deareſt <hi>Angelica,</hi> in withdrawing me by thy reaſons
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:171144:20"/>from the High Road that <hi>I</hi> was following. Few Perſons did prac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tice more than <hi>I</hi> did the moſt ſevere Mortifications; <hi>I</hi> have ſwing'd my ſelf off with Diſcipline, Blows, and Laſhes, often for to combat the in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nocent motions of Nature, which my Directour would needs per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwade me were horrible diſorders. Ah! have I been ſo miſtaken then? it is undoubtedly by the means of that cruel Maxime, That the miti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gated Orders are deſpiſed. Oh God, Do you thus ſuffer your name to be abuſed by unjuſt executions? and do you allow men to counterfeit you in this manner?</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Ang.</speaker>
               <p>Ah my poor child, I per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceive by theſe exclamations, that thou ſtill wanteſt ſome light, to ſee clearly and univerſally into all things; let us pauſe there; thy mind is not at preſent capable of a more nice ſpeculation. <hi>Love God and thy</hi> Neighbour, and believe that all the Law is contain'd in theſe two Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mandments.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <pb n="27" facs="tcp:171144:20"/>
               <speaker>Agn.</speaker>
               <p>How, <hi>Angelica,</hi> would you leave me in an errour?</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Ang.</speaker>
               <p>No, my pretty heart, thou ſhalt be fully inſtructed, and I will lend thee a Book which will per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fect thy Knowledg, and wherein thou wilt eaſily learn, what I ſhould not be able to explain to thee, with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out being out of Countenance.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Agn.</speaker>
               <p>Thats ſufficient; I muſt needs own I found this ſaying ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry pleaſant. <hi>That the Cloisters are the Common ſhoars, where Policy diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>charges it ſelf of it's ſuperfluities;</hi> Methinks one could not ſpeak after a more ſordid and more humbling manner?</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Ang.</speaker>
               <p>The Truth is, 'tis ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing a bold expreſſion; but it is not much more offenſive, than that of another, who ſaid, <hi>That the Fry<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ers and Nuns were in the Church, what the Rats and Mice were in the Ark of Noah.</hi>
               </p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Agn.</speaker>
               <p>Right, and I admire the eaſyneſs wherewith you utter your
<pb n="28" facs="tcp:171144:21"/>thoughts, I find I would not for all I may have moſt Dear, but that the opportunity of my doors be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing half open had given occaſion to our diſcourſe: yet I have com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prehended the ſence of all your Words.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Ang.</speaker>
               <p>Well! thou wilt then make a good uſe of 'em; and that beautiful Body, which is not cul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pable of any Crime, ſhall it ſtill be treated, as if it were the moſt in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>famous Criminal upon the Earth?</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Agn.</speaker>
               <p>No, I intend to give it ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tisfaction for what I have alrea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy made it ſuffer; I ask its par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>don, and particularly for a ſevere Diſcipline, which I but yeſterday in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>flicted upon it by order of my Confeſſour.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Ang.</speaker>
               <p>Kiſs me, my pretty Child, I am more moved with what thou telleſt me, than if I had made the tryal upon my ſelf; that puniſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment muſt be the laſt thou art to mortifie thy ſelf with: But prethee
<pb n="29" facs="tcp:171144:21"/>didſt thou hurt thy ſelf much?</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Agn.</speaker>
               <p>Alas! my zeal was indi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcreet, and I fancied the more ſtroaks that I gave, the more did I merit; my plump Body, and my youth rendered me ſenſible to the leaſt laſhes; ſo as at the end of this fair exerciſe, my Backſide was all of a Flame; nay, for ought I know I broke the fleſh, and made a wound, for that I was wholly tranſported, when I outraged it ſo cruelly.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Ang.</speaker>
               <p>My pretty little Dear, prid<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dee let me ſee and ſearch it, Ile ſee what an ill managed fervency is capable of?</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Agn.</speaker>
               <p>O Lord, Why muſt I ſuf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fer this? what you are then in earneſt? I cannot endure it without confuſion, Oh! Oh!</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Ang.</speaker>
               <p>Hey day, to what pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe then was all my diſcourſe, if thou art ſtill withheld by a ſilly Baſhfulneſs? What hurt is there in granting me my requeſt.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Agn.</speaker>
               <p>Indeed indeed I am to blame,
<pb n="30" facs="tcp:171144:22"/>and your Curioſity is not to be found fault with; ſatisfy it accord<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing to thy deſires.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Ang.</speaker>
               <p>So, ſo, this beautiful face that's alwayes vailed is now unco<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vered; get thee on thy knees on thy Bed, and douk down thy head a little that I may ſee the violence of thy Blows. Ah good Lord how 'tis ſtreaked! methinks I ſee <hi>Chyna Taf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fetas,</hi> or elſe the sky at Sun-Set<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing; you muſt needs be very de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vout at the <hi>Myſtery of Flagellation,</hi> ſince you ſcourge your Buttocks at this rate?</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Agn.</speaker>
               <p>Well now you have ſuffi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciently contemplated this innocent Outrage? Ah Lord what makes you grope there! Ah let it alone that it may recover its former com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plexion, and get rid of that ſtran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger of a colour. Pooh, what! do you kiſs it?</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Ang.</speaker>
               <p>Lye ſtill, my pretty Rogue, be not refractory, I have the moſt Compaſſionate ſoul in the World;
<pb n="31" facs="tcp:171144:22"/>and as it is a work of mercy to comfort the afflicted, Tis my Opi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nion that I cannot afford them too many Careſſes, for the worthily ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quitting my ſelf of that Duty. Ah! this part of thy Body is de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>licately well made: and what a Luſtre does it receive from its white<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs and plumpneſs; I perceive al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſo another part, which is no leſs well endowed by Nature; <hi>Tis Nature it ſelf.</hi>
               </p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Agn.</speaker>
               <p>Prethee take away thy hand from thence, if thou meaneſt not to cauſe there an inflamation which cannot eaſily be exſtinguiſhed? I <hi>I</hi> muſt needs own to thee my weak<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs, <hi>I</hi> am the moſt ſenſible Mai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>den that ever was, and what would not cauſe in others the leaſt Emo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, often puts me all in diſor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Ang.</speaker>
               <p>What then you are not of ſo cold a temper, as thou wouldeſt needs have perſwaded me at the be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ginning of the converſation? and
<pb n="32" facs="tcp:171144:23"/>I fancy thou wilt play thy part, as well as any one I know, when I have put thee into the hands of true honeſt Fryers; for this reaſon I would wiſh that the time of the retreat, I am going to enter into according to cuſtome, might be de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ferred, that ſo we might be toge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther in the Parlour: But no mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter, I ſhall comfort my ſelf with the account thou'lt give me of all that paſſes, namely, Whether the <hi>Abbot</hi> performs better than the <hi>Je<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſuite,</hi> or the <hi>Fryer</hi> than the <hi>Monk;</hi> and in ſhort, if all the whole Prieſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hood is able to give thee full ſatis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>faction.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Agn.</speaker>
               <p>Ah I fancy <hi>I</hi> ſhall be ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry much at a loſs in thoſe ſorts of entertainments, and that they will find me a mere Novice in point of Amours.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Ang.</speaker>
               <p>Trouble not your head, they know what courſe is to be ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken in ſuch occaſions, and a quar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter of an hour with them will ren<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der
<pb n="33" facs="tcp:171144:23"/>thee more knowing, than all the precepts thou mighteſt receive from me could do in a week. Come, cover your Back-ſide for fear thou ſhould'ſt catch cold; ſtay let me kiſs it once more, and again, and again.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Agn.</speaker>
               <p>Your are very wanton; do you think <hi>I</hi> would have born with theſe follies? no, but that <hi>I</hi> knew there was no hurt in all this.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Ang.</speaker>
               <p>If this was offending I ſhould ſin every moment, for the Schol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lars and Penſionaries, being com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitted to my care, obliges me to viſit their back apartments very often. But yeſterday I whipt one rather for my own ſatisfaction, than for any fault ſhe had committed; I took great delight in contempla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting her, ſhe is very pretty, and is already thirteen years of age.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Agn.</speaker>
               <p>I long for that employ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of Miſtriſs of the School, that I might take the like divertiſement! I have a mighty fancy to it, and I
<pb n="34" facs="tcp:171144:24"/>ſhould be overjoyed, might <hi>I</hi> ſee in what thou haſt ſo attentively con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſidered in my Perſon.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Ang.</speaker>
               <p>I am not at all ſurprized at thy requeſt, we are all made of the ſame Paſt. Hold I will put my ſelf into thy poſture; well now lift up my Pettecoats and my Smock as high as you can.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Ang.</speaker>
               <p>I have a great deſire to take my Diſcipline, and ſo order the buſineſs, that theſe two twin Siſters may have nothing to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>proach me with.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Ang.</speaker>
               <p>Oh! Oh, Oh, Hold! What do you do; theſe ſorts of ſports do not pleaſe me, but when they are not vio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lent? Hold, hold, if thy Devotion ſhould now happen to revive, I ſhould be undone! Oh God! <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>hou haſt a very flexible arm; <hi>I</hi> have a deſign to aſſociate thee in my Office, but you muſt uſe a little more Mode<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ration.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Agn.</speaker>
               <p>You have great reaſon indeed to complain, this is not the tenth part
<pb n="35" facs="tcp:171144:24"/>of the blows <hi>I</hi> have received; Ile defer the reſt till another time, ſomething muſt be allowed to thy little courage. Doſt thou know that this part becomes ſo much the more beautiful; a certain flame which a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nimates it, Communicates to it a Vermilion more bright and pure, than all that of <hi>Spain.</hi> Get a little nearer the window that the light may diſcover all its beauties—So, now its well, I could never be weary with looking on't. <hi>I</hi> ſee all <hi>I</hi> deſire, even its very neighbour<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hood. Why doſt cover that part with thy hand.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Ang.</speaker>
               <p>Alas, thou mayſt look ont as well as the Reſt; if there be a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny hurt in this occupation, yet it is not prejudicial to any Body, and does not any wiſe diſturb the pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lick tranquility.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Agn.</speaker>
               <p>How can it diſturb it, ſince we are no longer members of the publick? beſides faults concealed are half pardoned.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <pb n="36" facs="tcp:171144:25"/>
               <speaker>Ang.</speaker>
               <p>Thou haſt reaſon on thy ſide; for if as many faults were prac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiſed in the World (to ſpeak con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formably to our Rules,) as are com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitted in Cloiſters, Policy would be obliged to correct their abuſes, and put a ſtop to all their diſor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ders.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Agn.</speaker>
               <p>I alſo believe, that Fathers and Mothers would never ſuffer their Children to come into our Houſes, if they but knew the Diſ<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>orders that are committed there.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Ang.</speaker>
               <p>There's no doubt of that; but as moſt of the transgreſſions here are kept ſecret, and that Diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſimulation domineers more in Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vents, than in any other place, all thoſe who dwell in 'em do not per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceive the faults and diſorders, but ſerve themſelves to engage others. Beſides the particular intereſt of Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>milies does often get the better o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver many other Conſiderations.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Agn.</speaker>
               <p>The Confeſſours and Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rectours of Cloiſters have a peculi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ar
<pb n="37" facs="tcp:171144:25"/>talent to draw into their nets poor innocent Girls, who fall into a ſnare when they thought to have found a treaſure.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Ang</speaker>
               <p>True, and I have found it ſo in my own perſon. I had no inclination towards Religion, I diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>puted briskly againſt the reaſons of thoſe who perſwaded me to it; and I ſhould never have taken the vows, if a Jeſuite, who at that time governed this Monaſtery, had not undertook the matter. A Families concern obliged my Mother, who bare me a tender affection, who had alwayes oppoſed my being a Nun, to give her conſent to it; I reſiſted it a long time, becauſe I did not foreſee, that the <hi>Count de la Roche</hi> my eldeſt Brother, wh by right of Nobility, and the Cuſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>omes of the Country, would have for himſelf almoſt all the Eſtates and Riches of the Family, and that we being ſix of us left, without any other ſupport, than what he pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſed
<pb n="38" facs="tcp:171144:26"/>us, which according to his humour muſt have been but a ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry ſmall matter: At length he re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſigned a thouſand pounds, as he told me, of thoſe pretentions, to which were added four hundred more, ſo that I brought fourteen hundred Pounds in making my profeſſion in this Convent: But to return to the Cunning of him that drew me in, thou mayſt know the buſineſs was ſo ordered, that I met with him one afternoon, that I went to make a viſit to one of my Couzens who was a Nun, and who long'd to ſee me in the habit of a Religi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Agn.</speaker>
               <p>Was it not Siſter <hi>Victori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>a?</hi>
               </p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Ang.</speaker>
               <p>Ay the very ſame. Thus being all three in the ſame Parlour, <hi>Victoria</hi> and I, began with the com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pliments and civilities uſual in the Firſt interviews; they were follow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed with a diſcourſe of this <hi>Loyaliſt,</hi> touching the vanities of the age,
<pb n="39" facs="tcp:171144:26"/>and the difficulty of working out our own Salvation in the World; which did very much diſpoſe my mind to ſuffer it ſelf to be ſeduced: Theſe were nevertheleſs but ſlight pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>parations, he had many other ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tilties to inſinuate into my Boſom, and to make me eſpouſe the ſenti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments they lured me with: He told me ſometimes, that he obſerved in my Phyſiognomy the true Character of a Religious Soul; that he had a particular gift in the diſtinguiſhing thereof; and that I could not with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out doing an injury to God (ſo he ſaid) conſecrate to the World ſo perfect a Beauty as mine.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Agn.</speaker>
               <p>He took the right courſe; but what anſwer didſt thou make to all this?</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Ang.</speaker>
               <p>I preſently fell a combat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing theſe firſt Reaſons, by others which I oppoſed againſt him, which he deſtroyed with an admirable artifice. Beſides, <hi>Victoria</hi> was aid<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing to the deluding me, and ſhew'd
<pb n="40" facs="tcp:171144:27"/>me religion in ſuch coulours, as made it ſeem to have ſome Charms, and cunningly hid from me all that was capable of giving me any diſtaſte: In ſhort, the Jeſuite, who as I had learnt had made more difficult con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>queſts, uſed his utmoſt efforts to make ſure of mine. And was ſuc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſsful in his undertaking by the deſcription he gave me of the World and of Religions, and conſtrained me by the force of his Eloquence, ſtrictly to embrace his Party.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Ang.</speaker>
               <p>But prethee what ſaid he that was capable of exerciſing ſo abſolute a power over thy mind?</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Ang.</speaker>
               <p>I cannot tell thee all the Circumſtances for he held me three hours at the great; thou ſhalt on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly know, that he proved to me by Reaſons which I thought ſtrong, That this was my Vocation where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in alone I could attain to my Sal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vation; That there was no ſafety for me, nor way except that, that the World was full of, Rocks and Pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cipices;
<pb n="41" facs="tcp:171144:27"/>That the Exceſs of the Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligious was much better than the Moderation of the Worldly; That the repoſe and Contemplation of the former, was at the ſame time more delightful and more meritorious, than the action and all the Hurry of the latter; That it was in Cloiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters alone, that one could converſe familiarly with God; and by con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſequence to render ones ſelf wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thy of ſo Holy and ſo Excellent a Communication, we were to flye the Company of men. That it was in theſe places that the remnant of the Ancient Chriſtians were preſerved, and where might be ſeen the true Image of the primitive Church.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Ang.</speaker>
               <p>It was hardly poſſible to ſpeak with more Eloquence, and at the ſame time with more Cunning; for I obſerve that he ſaid not to thee a word of the rigors and Auſteri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tyes, that might ſtartle thee and di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vert thee from following the bait.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Ang.</speaker>
               <p>Thou art miſtaken; he for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>got
<pb n="42" facs="tcp:171144:28"/>nothing. But the Pains and Mortifications he told me of, were ſeaſoned with ſo much ſweetneſs, that I found 'em not diſtaſteful to my palate. I will hide nothing from you, ſaid he to me; theſe devout Societies, whoſe number I hope you will ſhortly augment, labour day and night by their Auſterities and Penances, to ſubdue the Pride and Inſolence of Nature: They exerciſe over their Senſes a violence which laſts alwayes; without dying their Soul is ſeparated from their Body; and equally deſpiſing grief and Vo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>luptuouſneſs, they live as if they were only made of the Spirit alone. This is not all, purſued he, with a perſwaſive tone, they make a rigo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rous Sacrifice of their Liberty, they ſtrip themſelves of all their goods to enrich themſelves only with hopes, and impoſe by ſolemn vows the neceſſity of a perpetual Vertue.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Agn.</speaker>
               <p>This Diſciple of <hi>Loyala,</hi> was a Maſter Orator, <hi>I</hi> wiſh <hi>I</hi> knew Him.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <pb n="43" facs="tcp:171144:28"/>
               <speaker>Agn.</speaker>
               <p>Thou knoweſt him well e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nough, and I will tell thee ſome ſmall circumſtances of his Life, which will make thee believe, that he knows how to play more than one part; But I muſt Firſt make an end of the reſt. You ſee, <hi>Made<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moiſelle,</hi> the Chains, Rigours, and Mortifications I offer you; but would you believe it, ſaid he to me, thoſe Holy Souls whereof I ſpoke to you juſt now, are proud of this Yoak, they Glory in this Servitude, and there is no manner of Severe Torment to ſuffer, but what they eſteem a great reward; they make all their Amours and Paſſion con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiſt in the Service of Jeſus Chriſt. It is he alone who puts 'em all in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to a Flame in caſe he does but touch e'm; It is he alone who is the on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly Maſter of their Hearts, and who knows how to make their Tor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments to be ſucceeded with incre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dible Joyes, Delights and Tran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſports.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <pb n="44" facs="tcp:171144:29"/>
               <speaker>Agn.</speaker>
               <p>Without doubt thou waſt charm'd with this florrid Talker.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Ang.</speaker>
               <p>Yes, my pretty Child, <hi>I</hi> was perſwaded by this Quack; His words changed me in a moment, they ſnatcht me from my ſelf, and made me eagerly court what <hi>I</hi> had con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtantly avoided: <hi>I</hi> became the moſt ſcrupulous perſon in the World; and becauſe he had told me, that out of the Cloiſter <hi>I</hi> could not work my Salvation, <hi>I</hi> imagined un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>til <hi>I</hi> was got into it, that <hi>I</hi> had all the Devils about me. Since that time he himſelf has endea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>voured to make me recover my Right Senſes, he has given me ſuch inſtructions, as were capable of freeing me out of the Errors he had plung'd me in, and it is to His Morals that I owe all the Repoſe and Quiet of mind that I now poſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeſs.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Agn.</speaker>
               <p>Prethee tell me quickly who this man is.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Ang.</speaker>
               <p>Tis Father <hi>Raucourt.</hi>
               </p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <pb n="45" facs="tcp:171144:29"/>
               <speaker>Agn.</speaker>
               <p>Ah Lord! He is an En<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chanter. I was once at Confeſſion to him, I took him for the moſt Devout man in the World; the Truth is, he knows to perfection the Art of inſinuating himſelf in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to peoples affections, and perſwades what he deſires. But I bear him a grudge, for having left me in the errour he found me in, and from whence he might have diſingaged me.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Ang.</speaker>
               <p>Ah! He is too prudent to run ſuch hazards! He ſaw thee un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der an extraordinary Bigottry, in horrible ſcruples, and knew that a Maiden is not ſo eaſily reduced from one extremity to the other. Be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſides if one Saint alone ſhould en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lighten all the Blind, there would be no more Miracles for others to do; thou underſtandeſt me? that is to ſay, If thou had hadſt Faith, thou wouldſt have been Cured, and that if that wiſe Directour had found in thee ſome diſpoſitions to follow his
<pb n="46" facs="tcp:171144:30"/>Ordinances, he would have been this Phiſician.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Agn.</speaker>
               <p>I believe it; but I had as lieve have the Obligation thereof to thee as to him. Tell me I be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeech thee, ſome Circumſtances of the Life of that Bleſſed Man?</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Ang.</speaker>
               <p>I will ſo, My Pretty Heart, but Kiſs me, and Embrace me very Amourouſly firſt: Ah! Ah! that's fine. Ah how am I charm'd with the Beauty of thy Mouth and Eyes! one of thy Kiſſes alone Tranſport me more than I am able to Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>p eſs!</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Agn.</speaker>
               <p>Begin then? Ah thou art a mighty Lover of Kiſſing!</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Ang.</speaker>
               <p>I am never weary of Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reſſing what is Lovely. Since you knew Father <hi>Raucourt,</hi> it is not neceſſary that I tell thee, that he is the man of the World, the moſt intriguing, the moſt Dextrous and the moſt ingenious that can be found. I will only tell thee, that in point of Amity, he is nice to the higheſt
<pb n="47" facs="tcp:171144:30"/>Degree, and as he ſets ſome va<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lue upon himſelf, many qualities are requiſite for to pleaſe him. Amongſt all his Conqueſts he rec<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>koned none more Glorious, than that he had made of a young <hi>Nun</hi> of a Convent in this City, who is called Siſter <hi>Virginia.</hi>
               </p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Agn.</speaker>
               <p>I have heard talk of her, as of a perfect Beauty, but I know no other Circumſtances of the Mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Ang.</speaker>
               <p>It is the Lovelieſt Perſon that can be ſeen, if the Picture her Gallant has ſhewed me of her be Faithful; as for Wit ſhe abounds with it as much as ſhe can deſire, ſhe is jocund and Facetious, Playes upon ſeveral Inſtruments, and Sings with Charms capable of bewitch<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing peoples Hearts. Our Jeſuite had already acquired her intirely to himſelf for ſome Months, and they both enjoyed that ſweet Tranqui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lity which makes all the Happineſs of Lovers; when Jealouſie began
<pb n="48" facs="tcp:171144:31"/>the diſorder I am going to tell you of.</p>
               <p>There was in the ſame <hi>Monaſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tery</hi> a <hi>Nun,</hi> for whom the Father had ſhewed ſome kindneſs, and to whom he had made ſeveral Viſits upon that deſign: He had alſo re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceived from her ſuch Favours, as were capable of engaging a man of the leaſt Fidelity: But the Luſtre of <hi>Virginia's</hi> Beauty, was too pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vailing over his Heart; he inward<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly diſengaged himſelf from that firſt commerce, and only afforded that poor Mayden, the outſide and appearance of a Real Love. She quickly perceived the change, and and ſaw clearly ſhe had a Rival, who ſhar'd with her in his offer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ings. She nevertheleſs diſſembled her ſpight and vexation; and ſeeing ſhe had to do with a Rival who ſurpaſſed her in all things, ſhe did not entertain the deſign of attacking her, but vowed the Ruine of him who deſpiſed her.</p>
               <p>To bring this Enterprize of hers
<pb n="49" facs="tcp:171144:31"/>the more eaſily about, ſhe Studied the Houres and Moments that <hi>Vir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ginia</hi> met with this Religious Lo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver; and as ſhe had learnt by ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perience, that he did not content himſelf with Words, nor light Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vors, ſhe fancyed ſhe might reaſona<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bly ſurprize them in certain Exerci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes, the Knowledg whereof rendred her Miſtriſs of the fate of her faith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſs Lover: She was a long while before ſhe could diſcover any thing ſtrong enough: She perceived in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deed two or three times that poor Father warming his hand in <hi>Vir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ginia's</hi> Boſome: She ſaw e'm In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terchange ſome Kiſſes with an in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>credible fervency; but this paſſed for trifles in her mind; and as ſhe knew that theſe ſorts of Actions were in Cloyſters only reckoned for Pocadilloes, which Holy Waters waſhes clean; ſhe held her peace, waiting for a better Occaſion to ſpeak.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Agn.</speaker>
               <p>Ah I am in a terrible fright
<pb n="50" facs="tcp:171144:32"/>for poor <hi>Virginia!</hi>
               </p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Ang.</speaker>
               <p>Our Lovers not in the leaſt ſuſpecting the Ambuſhes that were laid for them, took no meaſures to avoid them: They met two or three times a Week, and wrote Letters when Prudence Obliged them to part for ſome time from one ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther. The Fathers Letters, whoſe expreſſions are tender and paſſio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nate made a perfect conqueſt over <hi>Virginia.</hi> He went to ſee her af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter eight dayes abſence, and ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerved he ſhould obtain from her what ſhe had alwayes refuſed him before. In the mean while her Rival was not Idle, for Correſpond<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing with the Matron that was the Door-Keeper, ſhe had notice of the Jeſuites arrival, and not doubting but that after ſo long an interval, they would proceed to ſuch priva<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cies, as ſhe could have wiſhed for her ſelf, ſhe went Tranſported with a Jealouſy into a Nook hard by the Parlour, where by the means of a
<pb n="51" facs="tcp:171144:32"/>little Chink ſhe had made, ſhe might diſcover to the very leaſt motions of thoſe who entertained one another there, and hear their moſt ſecret Converſations.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Agn.</speaker>
               <p>Now does my fear revive! Ah I have a ſpight againſt that Cu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rious Creature for diſturbing ſo ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liciouſly the Repoſe of two un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>happy Lovers!</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Ang.</speaker>
               <p>That the Depoſitions ſhe deſigned to make of what ſhe ſaw, might be the more Authentick, and received without difficulty, ſhe took another <hi>Nun</hi> with her, who might give the ſame Evidence. Being thus, both poſted in the place I mentioned, they perceived our two Lovers entertaining one another more by their looks and their ſighs, than by Words; they graſped one anothers hands, and with languiſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing looks ſpake ſome tender words, which departed more from their Hearts than from their Mouth. This Amorous Contemplation followed
<pb n="52" facs="tcp:171144:33"/>with opening a little four ſquare Caſement, which was toward the midſt of the grate, and which ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved for pretty big Packquets to paſs through of ſuch as made preſents to the <hi>Nuns:</hi> Then it was that <hi>Vir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ginia,</hi> received and gave a thouſand Kiſſes, but with ſuch great Tranſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ports, ſuch ſurprizing ſaillies, that Love it ſelf could not have aug<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mented the ardour of them; Ah my dear <hi>Virginia,</hi> began my Paſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>onate Prieſt, would you have us ſtop here? Alas! What ſmall re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turns do you make to thoſe who Love you, and how well do you practiſe the art of tormenting them? Alas! How, replyed our Veſtal, can I make you any other pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent after having given you my Heart? Ah! How Tyrannical is your Love! I know what you de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſire, I know too that I have had the weakneſs to make you hope for it, but neither am I ignorant, that it is all my Bleſſing and all my Ri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ches,
<pb n="53" facs="tcp:171144:33"/>and that I cannot grant it you but by reducing my ſelf to Extre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mity. Cannot we remain in the terms we are under, paſs together ſoft delightful moments, and enjoy Pleaſures ſo much the more per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fect, as they are Pue and Inno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cent? If your Happineſs, as you ſay, does only depend on what I have moſt dear, you can be hap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>py but once, and I alwayes miſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rable, ſince it is a thing that can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not be recovered. Believe me, let us Love as a Brother Loves a Siſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter, and let us allow this Love all the freedom that can be imagined, with exception to one alone.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Agn.</speaker>
               <p>And what anſwer did the <hi>Jeſuite</hi> make to all this?</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Ang.</speaker>
               <p>During the Diſcourſe he ſaid not a Word, but leaning with his head on one of his hands, he look't with Eyes full of Languiſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment on her who ſpoke to him; after which, taking her by the hand through the grate, he told her after
<pb n="54" facs="tcp:171144:34"/>a touching manner! Muſt we then change our Method, and no longer Love as before? Can you conſent to this <hi>Virginia,</hi> for my part I can retrench nothing of my Love, and the Rules you have newly pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcribed to me, not to be received by a true Lover. He exaggerated to her afterward, with ſo much heat, the exceſs of his Flames, that he ab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolutely diſconcerted her; and drew from her an Oral Promiſe, of grant<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing him within ſome few days, what alone would render him perfectly happy. He then made her come nearer to the grate, and having made her mount upon a pretty high ſtool, he conjured her to allow him, at leaſt to ſatisfie his ſight, ſince he was barred all other Liberty; ſhe obeyed him after ſome reſiſtance, and ſuffered him to ſee and grope the parts conſecrated to Chaſtity, and Continency. She for her part would alſo needs ſatisfie her eyes with the like Curioſity, and the
<pb n="55" facs="tcp:171144:34"/>
                  <hi>Jeſuite</hi> who was not inſenſible, eaſily found the means for her ſo doing, ſhe obtained from him what ſhe deſired with more eaſineſs than ſhe granted his requeſt. Then was the fatal moments of 'em both, and what our Spyes deſired: They con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>templated with an extraordinary ſatisfaction, the fine parts of their Companions Body, which the <hi>Jeſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ite</hi> laid to view, and felt and gro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ped with tranſports of an enchan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted Lover: Sometimes they Admi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red one part, and ſometimes ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, according as the Officious Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther turned and changed the ſcitu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ation of his Miſtriſs; ſo that when he conſidered the fore part, he ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſed her Breech to the light, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe her Petticoats all round were lifted &amp; tuckt up above her middle.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Agn.</speaker>
               <p>Methinks I am preſent at this ſpectacle, ſo naturally doſt thou tell the Story!</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Ang.</speaker>
               <p>At length they terminated their wantonings, and our two Siſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters
<pb n="56" facs="tcp:171144:35"/>retired with a deſign to put a ſtop to theſe ill managed Amours, and to hinder the effect of <hi>Virgi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nia's</hi> promiſe. By a particular hap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pineſs for that Poor innocent Crea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture, the <hi>Nun,</hi> whom her Rival had aſſociated to her in the Conſide<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ration of what had paſſed, had a very tender kindneſs for her, and endeavoured to find a byaſs for Ruining the <hi>Jeſuite,</hi> without inju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring her ſhe loved; ſhe gave her to underſtand what ſhe knew of her interigues, aſſured her of doing nothing to her prejudice, provi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded ſhe would promiſe her to break intirely off with that <hi>Prieſt,</hi> and not have for the future the leaſt Communication with him. <hi>Virginia</hi> extreamly aſhamed at what ſhe heard, engaged her ſelf to all that was deſired, only earneſtly begs the <hi>Jeſuites</hi> Reputation may be ſaved, becauſe it was impoſſible to wound the one, without doing ſome damage to the other; ſhe pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teſted
<pb n="57" facs="tcp:171144:35"/>ſhe would ſee him no more, and that the Letter ſhe was going to write to him never to return again, ſhould be the Laſt he ſhould re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceive from her. Theſe conditions were accepted by both, though with trouble; they embrace <hi>Virginia,</hi> of whom they were become Enamour<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, and ſaid at parting, that they would ſupply the Fathers place, and enter into a ſtrict friendſhip with her.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Agn.</speaker>
               <p>She came off then at a pretty cheap Rate, I fancy ſhe ow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed this indulgence to her Beauty, and to her other qualities, which rendered her without doubt Ami<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>able to her very Enemy?</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Ang.</speaker>
               <p>We are not yet at the end of our Hiſtory. <hi>Virginia</hi> imediatly wrote a Letter to Father <hi>Raucourt,</hi> &amp; there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in acquainted him with all that had happened, and with the Conditions ſhe had bound her ſelf to, to ſave both her and his Honour; ſhe re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monſtrated to him the danger he
<pb n="58" facs="tcp:171144:36"/>would expoſe himſelf to, if he came to ſee her again; and lett him al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſo know, that it was impoſſible ſhe could receive any of his Letters, un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſs he made uſe of a particular trick, to avoid their being ſurprized; ſhe ended with proteſtations of a con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtant Love and proof againſt all the moſt ſecret attacks of Jealouſy, and made him hope, that time would diſſipate that ſtorm, which threat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned them. I do not ſay with what ſurprize this Father received and read this Letter, which ſtruck him, as it were, with a Thunder-Bolt, he ſaw it was not convenient to make any Anſwer to it, and that he muſt be forc'd to buckle to an an unhappy Accident, which op<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſed his good Fortune, in the ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry moment he was ready to enjoy it.</p>
               <p>Three Weeks was already paſs'd of this Widdow-hood, when <hi>Vir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ginia</hi> growing weary of that ſoli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tary Life, found by a marvellous
<pb n="59" facs="tcp:171144:36"/>piece of cunning, the means of hearing from her Lover, and letting him hear from her: She preten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded to have forgotten to ſend Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther <hi>Raucourt</hi> a ſquare Bonnet, which he had given her to make in the time of their late Familiari<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties. Her Rival told her, that ſhe needed but to give it to her, and that ſhe would have it delivered to her by a <hi>Touriere.</hi> This was done accordingly, the meſſenger had no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tice after what manner ſhe was to ſpeak to him; ſhe acquitted her ſelf punctually of her Commiſſion, and the <hi>Jeſuite</hi> after he had recei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved the Bonnet, he deſired her to wait a moment in the Church, that he might have time to think of what he ſaw. After ſome ſmall reflection, he ſuſpected the ſtrata<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gem, ript open the Bonnet in a certain place, and there found <hi>Vir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ginia</hi>'s Letter: Without examining it much, he made a ſpeedy anſwer to it, which he put in the ſame
<pb n="60" facs="tcp:171144:37"/>place, and clos'd it up the beſt he could, with two or three ſtitches of a needle: he came again to the <hi>Touriere,</hi> whom he deſired to carry back the Bonnet, that it might be mended, becauſe that it was much too narrow for him; that he had tryed it upon ſeveral other of the Convent, that he might exempt the Perſon from the trouble ſhe might have in reforming it, but that there was not a Father it fit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted; that for the reſt he was obliged to her for the Patience ſhe had had to wait ſo long. The good Siſter made anſwer by her Bows to the Fathers Civilityes, and car<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ryed back the four ſquar'd Bonnet to the Monaſtery, deliver'd it by order of her, who ſent her into the hands of <hi>Virginia,</hi> who was over<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>joyed to hear there the news of him ſhe loved, and for that her Artifice had had ſuch good ſuc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſs.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Agn.</speaker>
               <p>It muſt be confeſſed that
<pb n="61" facs="tcp:171144:37"/>Love is full of Invention.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Ang.</speaker>
               <p>This Commerce laſted for above a Month, there was ſtill ſom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing to be altered and mended in this Venerable Bonnet; once in three days it was to be carryed to the <hi>Colledge</hi> and back again to the <hi>Monastery.</hi> Yet no body imagin'd that there was any My<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtery in ſuch a thing as that; no notice was taken of it; and they might ſtill have made uſe of this Poſtilion, had it not been for this accident which ſpoiled all.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Agn.</speaker>
               <p>Oh Lord, I fancy the whole Plot was diſcovered by the <hi>Tou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riere.</hi>
               </p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Ang.</speaker>
               <p>No, thou art miſtaken. It happened that on a faſt day, that the Porter of the <hi>Jeſuites</hi> was out of humour, perhaps for that he had not ſtuffed his Gutts, at his uſual Rate: The <hi>Touriere</hi> who had an infinite number of Commiſſions, and amongſt others that of the Bon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>net, rang twice or thrice at the
<pb n="62" facs="tcp:171144:38"/>
                  <hi>Colledg Gate,</hi> for to diſcharge her ſelf as ſoon as poſſible of her Meſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſage. This good <hi>Fryer</hi> went out of the Garden he was in, and be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing come almoſt out of Breath; thinking it was the Biſhop or Arch-Biſhop, or ſome other Grandee, who had rung after ſo Command<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing a manner, was much ſurpriz<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed at the ſight of the poor Siſter; ſhe had nothing elſe to ſay to him, than to deliver the four ſquare Bonnet into the hands of Father <hi>De Raucourt.</hi> This pettiſh man being vex'd at ſo many trouble<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſome viſits, upon ſo ſmall a mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter, fell into a Paſſion, and ſaid; That Bonnet walked very often, and that he would put it into the hands of a man who ſhould make it withdraw for a while. The <hi>Tou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riere</hi> excuſing her ſelf as well as ſhe could, away ſhe went, and the Rector waiting for a Companion in the Porters Lodge to go out to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gether, having heard the Dialogue,
<pb n="63" facs="tcp:171144:38"/>called the Brother, and would needs know the ſubject of the diſpute, and why he treated ſo rudely the Perſons who had buſineſs with thoſe of the <hi>Colledg.</hi> This man, ſeeing himſelf ſchool'd by his Superior, told him all he thought of this Bonnet; told him that it had already jogg'd &amp; jaunted above 20. times between the <hi>Colledge</hi> and the <hi>Monaſtery:</hi> that there muſt without doubt be ſome hidden deſign in this matter; and that if His Reverence was ſo pleaſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, he would ſearch the Cap which he ſaid was counter-band; which he did at that ſame inſtant, and with one touch with his Ciſſars he brought to light the <hi>Fifteenth In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fant of the ſquare Bonnet,</hi> which came in a direct Line from Siſter <hi>Vir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ginia.</hi>
               </p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Agn.</speaker>
               <p>Oh Lord! how difficult a matter it is to ſave ones ſelf, when purſued by an ill Deſtiny, and that it has ſworn ones ruine. What hap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pened of all this buſineſs?</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <pb n="64" facs="tcp:171144:39"/>
               <speaker>Ang.</speaker>
               <p>It happened that the Father was confined into another province, and that poor <hi>Virginia</hi> has been mortifyed with ſome Penances; from hence came that Proverb, <hi>That there is a great deal of malice under a Jeſuits four ſquare Bonnet.</hi>
               </p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Agn.</speaker>
               <p>Good Lord! It was for her alone that I was in fear, but tell me how this came to the know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge of the <hi>Prioreſs?</hi>
               </p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Ang.</speaker>
               <p>I ſhould be too tedious in entertaining thee with one and the ſame thing; In the firſt Converſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion after my retreat, I will tell thee more upon this Subject; I will ſhew thee two Infants of the four ſquar'd Bonnet, and will acquaint thee with the Fate of their Father and Mother. Think only at preſent, my Deareſt, that I am going to ſpend eight or ten dayes after a very doleful manner, ſince I ſhall be barred having the leaſt confe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rence with thee; I am going to write to my three honeſt Friends
<pb n="65" facs="tcp:171144:39"/>that they may Viſit thee during that time: There is an Abbot, a Fryer, and a Capuchine.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Agn.</speaker>
               <p>What a mixture! and what wouldeſt thou have me do with all thoſe people whom I know not?</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Ang.</speaker>
               <p>Thou needeſt only be Obe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dient, they will teach thee ſuffici<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ently what ſhall be thy Duty, for the ſatisfying and contenting them. Here, take this Book I lend thee, make a good uſe of it, it will inſtruct thee with many things, and will give thy mind all the quiet thou canſt wiſh for. Kiſs me my poor Child, Kiſs me for all the time I am to be abſent. I ſhould paſs my retreat after a very pleaſant rate, If my Derectour was as Amiable and as Docible as thou art. <hi>Adieu.</hi> My heart, Dreſs thee, and be ſure that thou keepeſt all our amorours mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters ſecret, and prepare thy ſelf to give me an account of all thy Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vertiſements when my Exerciſes are expired.</p>
            </sp>
            <trailer>End of the Firſt Dialogue.</trailer>
         </div>
         <div n="2" type="dialogue">
            <pb facs="tcp:171144:40"/>
            <pb n="67" facs="tcp:171144:40"/>
            <head>
               <hi>Venus</hi> in the <hi>Cloister,</hi> OR THE <hi>Nun</hi> in Her <hi>Smock.</hi>
            </head>
            <head type="sub">Second <hi>Dialogue.</hi>
            </head>
            <stage>Siſter <hi>Angelica,</hi> Siſter <hi>Agnes.</hi>
            </stage>
            <sp>
               <speaker>ANgelica.</speaker>
               <p>Ah! God be Praiſed, I begin to breath again; never was I more peſtered with De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>votions, Myſteries and Indulgences, than ſince I left thee; I nauſeate ſtrangely all thoſe Superſtitions. How doſt do? What not a Word? Why do you Laugh?</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Agnes.</speaker>
               <p>
                  <hi>I</hi> am quite aſhamed to appear before your eyes again; I
<pb n="68" facs="tcp:171144:41"/>fancy you know all, to the very leaſt particulars, of what has been ſaid, and done, ſince your abſence.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Ang.</speaker>
               <p>And who ſhou'd tell it me? What you railly me? Come, come thy wayes into my Room, and think where you are to begin to give me a faithful Narrative. For my part I came out of the hands of a ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vage Creature, who would have made a perſon of any other hu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mour than mine mad, I mean my Directour; It is the worſt natur'd, and moſt ignorant man of his Cha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>racter. I fancy he has made me gain all the Indulgences and Par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dons that were ever granted by the Popes, ſince <hi>Gregory</hi> the Great to <hi>Innocent</hi> the XI. If I had followed his Order, I had ſet my Body in Blood by the Diſcipline he preſcri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bed me; not that I let him ſee much malice in the confeſſions I made him, but becauſe he imagines, that to be in the way of Paradice, one muſt be as dry, as lean, and
<pb n="69" facs="tcp:171144:41"/>as fleſhleſs as himſelf; and that it is ſufficient to be ſomething chear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful and plump to merit all manner of Penances. Judge now, how I have ſpont my time, and if I had not reaſon to think it tedious?</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Agn.</speaker>
               <p>For my part I muſt tell thee, that thou haſt given me Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rectours, who have tyred me little leſs than thine have done; I know not if I have gain'd Indulgences with 'em; but I am certain that to gain them, many Perſons do not do ſo much as we have done.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Ang.</speaker>
               <p>That I do not doubt of. But tell me a litle News of our Abbot, and let me know if he is capable of any great matter.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Agn.</speaker>
               <p>Him it was, I firſt ſaw, and in whom I found the moſt heat; there is nothing more lively, and more animated, and there's ple<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure in hearing him diſcourſe. I was at the afternoons Recreation, when word was brought me, that he ask'd to ſpeak with me. As I knew the Lady
<pb n="70" facs="tcp:171144:42"/>
                  <hi>Abbeſs</hi> was indiſpoſed, I ſent him word by the Porter, that he ſhould go into the Great Parlour, and that he would not grow impatient. I made him wait for a large quar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter of an hour, becauſe I changed my Vail, and ſome other things, that I might appear the Neater before him, and endeavour to an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwer the hopes he had of ſeeing a Perſon, of whom he had heard ſo advantageous a Deſcription. At the firſt I ſeem'd ſomething mute and ſilent, anſwering very ſeriouſly to the civilities he paid me, but this did not diſcourage him; on the contrary he took an occaſion to tell me very boldly, that he knew the Fair Ladies had the freedom to ſpeak after a certain indifferent manner, which would be unbecom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing in others; but that he had rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon to hope, that preſenting him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf under the Favour and Recom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mendation of my beſt Friend, his Viſit could not but be grateful to me.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <pb n="71" facs="tcp:171144:42"/>
               <speaker>Agn.</speaker>
               <p>He paſſes for a Witt; and we may ſay that his great Tra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vels accompanyed with much ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perience, have added to his natu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ral advantages all the perfection he had wanting.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Agn.</speaker>
               <p>I know not what thou hadſt told him of me, but I found he made great Progreſs for a firſt Viſit! He turned the Converſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion upon the Auſterity of Religi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous Houſes, and endeavoured to per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwade me by an infinite number of Reaſons, not to follow the in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diſcreet Zeal of ſeveral, terming all thoſe ridiculous, who indifferently put in practice all ſorts of Morti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fications. He made me laugh at the Natural account he gave me, of what hapned to him in <hi>Italy</hi> with a <hi>Nun</hi> of St. <hi>Bennet,</hi> of whoſe cun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning he made uſe of to ſee her as often as he pleas'd, and how at length he received ſuch favours from her, as were to be the effect of his Aſſiduities. He aſſured me that be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore
<pb n="72" facs="tcp:171144:43"/>that acquaintance, he had al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wayes believed, it was only amongſt the Nuns that the true Veſtal Chaſtity was preſerved, and that he had alwayes perſwaded him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf, that thoſe recluſe Souls, lived in ſo perfect a Continency, as that of the Angels; but that he had found the contrary, and that nothing per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fect is meanly ſpoiled; and that a thing keeps in its Corruption, the ſame degree it had in its Goodneſs; he had obſerved there was nothing more diſſolute than all the Recluſed and Bigots, when they find occa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion to divert themſelves. He ſhew<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed me a certain Inſtrument of Glaſs, which he had received from her, whom I have ſpoke to thee of, and aſſured me, that he had learnt from her, there were above fifty of the ſame in the <hi>Monaſtery,</hi> and that all from the <hi>Abbeſs</hi> to the laſt Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſour managed it oftner than their Beads.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Ang.</speaker>
               <p>That's fine! but thou tel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſt
<pb n="73" facs="tcp:171144:43"/>me nothing of what concerns thy ſelf.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Agn.</speaker>
               <p>What wouldeſt thou have me tell thee? He is the moſt wan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ton man upon the face of the earth. At the ſecond viſit he made me, I could not diſpence my ſelf from granting him ſome favour; he op<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſed all my reaſons with Morals ſo ſtrong, and ſo full of artifice, that he rendered all my Efforts uſeleſs and to no purpoſe: He ſhew<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed me three Letters from our <hi>Ab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>beſs,</hi> which aſſured me that let me do what I would, I ſhould only walk in her ſteps. She has ſpent whole nights with him, and only terms him in her Letters the <hi>Ab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bot</hi> of <hi>Loves Paradice.</hi> I repreſen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted to him, that the Grate was an inſurmountable obſtacle, and that he muſt of neceſſity con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tent himſelf with ſome ſlight wan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tonings, ſince it was impoſſible to proceed any farther. But he gave me ſufficiently to underſtand, that he
<pb n="74" facs="tcp:171144:44"/>was much more knowing than I, and ſhewed me two Boards, that were to be lifted up, the one on his ſide and the other on mine, and which gave ſufficient paſſage for a Perſon: He told me that it was by his advice, that the Lady <hi>Abbeſs</hi> had ſo ordered the buſineſs, that ſhe had call'd it the <hi>Streight</hi> of <hi>Gilbraltar,</hi> and that ſhe one day told him, that he muſt not ven<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture paſſing it without being well provided with all things neceſſary, particularly if he had any deſigne to ſtop at the Pillars of <hi>Hercules.</hi> Thus after ſeveral conteſts on both Sides, The <hi>Abbot</hi> paſſ'd the <hi>Streight,</hi> and arrived at the Port where he was received, but it was not without difficulty, and only after having aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſured me that his entrance ſhould have no ill conſequence; I allow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed him to ancher as long as was neceſſary to render him happy; it was the ſeventh of the <hi>Month</hi> of <hi>Auguſt,</hi> which was a day that my
<pb n="75" facs="tcp:171144:44"/>Lady <hi>Abbeſs</hi> was uſed to be Employed in great Ceremonies, but that her indiſpoſition had obliged to defer till the next <hi>Month</hi> following what ſhe commonly obſerved in this. He told me that ſhe had created the ſecond year ſhe was <hi>Abbeſs</hi> an Or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der of Knighthood, which was compos'd only of <hi>Priests, Monks,</hi> and <hi>Abbots,</hi> and Religious and E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cleſiaſtical Perſons. That thoſe who were admitted into it, took an Oath to keep the ſecret of the Order, and call'd themſelves the Knights of the <hi>Grate,</hi> or of St. <hi>Lau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rence;</hi> that the Coulour which was given them at the day of their Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ception, was compos'd of the Cy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phers of my Lady <hi>Abbeſs,</hi> interwo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven with Flames of Love, and that below hung a Medal of Gold, Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſenting the Patron of the Order, lying all naked upon a <hi>Grate,</hi> in the midſt of Flames, with theſe Words, <hi>Ardorem Craticula Fovet,</hi> That is to ſay, <hi>The Grate Augments
<pb n="76" facs="tcp:171144:45"/>my Heat.</hi> He ſhewed me the Col<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lar he had received, and after he had made me ſome preſents of cu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rious Books, we parted from one another until a new Interview.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Ang.</speaker>
               <p>Thou haſt told me nothing now touching this Order eſtabliſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed by my Lady <hi>Abbeſs;</hi> my Lord Biſhop of <g ref="char:cross">✚</g>
                  <g ref="char:cross">✚</g>
                  <g ref="char:cross">✚</g>, is the Firſt Knight of it, the <hi>Abbot de Beaumont</hi> the Second, the <hi>Abbot du Prat</hi> the Third, the <hi>Prior de Pompiere</hi> the Fourth; theſe are the Principals and the Firſt in date; they are followed by <hi>Jeſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ites,</hi> by <hi>Jacobins, Auguſtins, Carme<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lites,</hi> Fathers of the <hi>Oratory,</hi> and the Provincial of the <hi>Cordeli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ers.</hi> So as at the laſt Promotion, which was made in the year laſt paſt, the Number was Twenty-two. But it is obſervable, that there is a great deal of difference between them, and that they cannot all en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>joy equal Priviledges; there are of them who call themſelves the <hi>Blew Ribonds,</hi> and theſe are thoſe
<pb n="77" facs="tcp:171144:45"/>who are the <hi>Almightyes,</hi> who have the ſecret of the Order, and who diſpoſe of my Lady <hi>Abbeſſes</hi> affairs as my Lady <hi>Abbeſs</hi> manages theirs. As for the others their Power is li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mited, it has bounds which they cannot paſs. And they have little more advantage than the Aſpirers, until that by their Zeal, their Pru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dence and their Diſcretion, they have rendered themſelves worthy of being of the Great Profeſſion. Of all the <hi>Monks,</hi> the <hi>Capuchins</hi> alone are excluded, becauſe the Beardwhich diſguiſes them ſo much, has rendered them Odious to our <hi>Abbeſs,</hi> who ſayes, that ſhe cannot imagine that any Perſon of our Sex can bear any Good Will to thoſe Satyres. But to the purpoſe tell me ſome tydings of Father <hi>Vital</hi> of <hi>Charenton.</hi>
               </p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Agn.</speaker>
               <p>I ſhould never have believed no more than my Lady <hi>Abbeſs,</hi> that a <hi>Capuchin,</hi> could have been ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pable of a Gallantry, if this man
<pb n="78" facs="tcp:171144:46"/>had not perſwaded me of it by his Conduct. He came to ſee me three dayes after our <hi>Abbot,</hi> we went in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to the Parlour of St. <hi>Auguſtin,</hi> and there it was that he tickled my fan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cy with ſo many wanton diſcour<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces, that I could not have expect<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed more from a profeſsed Courti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er. Beſides, he ſpoke ſo boldly that I was aſham'd to hear come out of the mouth of a man, words at firſt ſomthing <hi>Li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bertine,</hi> but at length the moſt diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolute the greateſt Debauchee could have made uſe of. I could not forbear making him ſenſible of my aſtoniſhment, and letting him know, that there was exceſs in his tran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſports; which made him uſe ſome moderation in the matter. He made me three viſits during thy retreat, and at the laſt he obtained no great Favours from me, becauſe the Parlour where we were had not the conveniencies of the others. I will only tell thee, that he prepa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red
<pb n="79" facs="tcp:171144:46"/>me ſufficient matter to laugh at, in that having by his efforts looſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned one of the Bars of the Iron in the Grate, and thinking he had made a paſſage ſufficiently large, to paſs through it, he ventured, not<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>withſtanding my diſſwaſions: But through he could not get, for as much as having paſſed his head, and one of his ſhoulders with a great deal of difficulty, his Cowle got hold of one of the ſpikes with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out, ſo notwithſtanding all his ſtrug<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling he could not get rid of that ſnare. I could not contemplate him in that poſture, without burſting out a laughing, I made him get back again as ſoon as he could, and caus'd him to put the Grate ſo as it was before. He gave me three or four Books which he had mention'd to me in his firſt Viſit, and withdrew very ill ſatisfied with his Adven<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Ang.</speaker>
               <p>I am ſorry for this diſor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der, for without doubt this will have diſcourag'd him.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <pb n="80" facs="tcp:171144:47"/>
               <speaker>Agn.</speaker>
               <p>Diſcourag'd him! Good Lord! He's no man, take my word, to be diſcouraged; he is the moſt impudent and moſt diſſolute of all men; I hope hee'l be here yet be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore the Weeks at an end, he has promiſed me the <hi>Collection of the ſecret Amours of Robertd, Abriſſel;</hi> he began to tell me the ſtory, but I can't believe its true, it muſt needs be a piece of Invention.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Ang.</speaker>
               <p>Thou'rt miſtaken, there is nothing more true; and ſeveral grave Authors write, that he was uſed to Lye with his <hi>Nuns</hi> that he might try 'em, and obſerve at the ſame time in his own Perſon, how far the ſtrength of vertue can pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vail, which combate the tempta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions of the fleſh; he thought this very meritorious in him, and this it was that gave occaſion to <hi>God<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>frey</hi> of <hi>Vendome,</hi> to term this De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>votion pleaſant and ridiculous, in a Letter he wrote to St. <hi>Bernard,</hi> and calls this fervency a new kind of
<pb n="81" facs="tcp:171144:47"/>Martyrdome; This has hitherto been the occaſion of that mans not being placed in the Calender of the Saints by the Court of <hi>Rome,</hi> he is nevertheleſs term'd Bleſſed.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Agn.</speaker>
               <p>We muſt own, that there are many abuſes practiſed in our Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligion, and I am not now at all ſurprized, that ſo many Nations have ſeparated themſelves from our Church, to apply themſelves litte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rally to the Scriptures. The Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther <hi>Mendicant</hi> whom I ſaw du<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring thy retreat, made me Viſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bly remark all the faults of the pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent Government, as to what con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerns Religion: he is a man who for his Age, (for he is not yet <hi>Six</hi> and <hi>Twenty</hi> Years Old) poſſeſſes all the Sciences that can render a perſon accompliſhed of what Cha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>racter ſoever he may be; he ſpeaks Univerſally upon all ſubjects, but with ſo eaſy an air that Savours nothing of the <hi>Pedant.</hi>
               </p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Ang.</speaker>
               <p>I perceive thou art pleas<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed
<pb n="82" facs="tcp:171144:48"/>with him, he is well made, and a luſty handſome <hi>Sawny,</hi> for my part I always call him my <hi>ſwinging Towzer;</hi> in what Parlour ſaweſt thou him?</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Agn.</speaker>
               <p>I ſaw him twice, he firſt was in the Parlour of St. <hi>Joſeph,</hi> and the laſt was in that of my La<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy <hi>Abbeſs.</hi>
               </p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Ang.</speaker>
               <p>Well, well, that is to ſay, he paſs'd the <hi>Streigths,</hi> he well de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerved it, and there's delight in ſee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing him play his part.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Agn.</speaker>
               <p>He gave me two ſmall vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>alls of Eſſence, which have a won<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derful Odour, he was perfumed from top to toe, and with ſo Animated a Vermilion, that I at firſt ſuſpect<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed he had been at the little pot; but I found the contrary afterwards, and ſaw that the Red only pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceeded from the fervency of his Paſſion. I was infinitely pleaſed with his diſcourſe, and his way of toying and wantoning, and I made no difficulty of granting him the
<pb n="83" facs="tcp:171144:48"/>paſſage I had ſo much diſputed with our <hi>Abbot.</hi> I repreſented to him, that there was reaſon to fear, that the follies we two committed would be followed with a third: I un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derſtand you, replyed he, and at the ſame time took a little Book out of his pocket which he gave me, the title of it was, <hi>Soft and ea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſy Remedies againſt dangerous ſwel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling.</hi> He told me it would teach me what I had to do in ſuch an occaſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, he put a little Conſerve into my mouth, which I found had no ill taſte; I know not if it contain'd any ſecret Vertue, but immediate<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly he put himſelf into a poſture of attacking the Pillars of <hi>Hercules.</hi>
               </p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Ang.</speaker>
               <p>That is to ſay, ſwinging <hi>Towzer</hi> won thy Heart.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Agn.</speaker>
               <p>Certain it is that he ſhar'd it with the <hi>Abbot;</hi> I cannot tell thee to whom I could give the prefer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rence: One thing alone diſpleaſed me in the <hi>Mendicant,</hi> which is, that having ſeen about his neck a
<pb n="84" facs="tcp:171144:49"/>Reliquary of Guilt Vermilion, which he wore upon his heart; I had the curioſity to open it, but I was very much ſurprized to find no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing elſe, than a kind of a down, and hairs of different colours, di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vided into Figures and Flowers in ſeveral Branches, and very well done. He own'd to me that theſe were the Favours of all his Miſtreſſes, and deſired me to countenance like<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe his Devotion with the like, and that what I ſhould bleſs him with a grant of ſhould be put in the fineſt place of all! Well in ſhort I complyed with his humour! I forgot to tell thee that there was in Characters of Gold, this inſcrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion in the midſt of a Chriſtal which covered all this fine Mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>handizes, <hi>Relicks of the Holy Beard.</hi> Upon the outſide of the Reliquary there was Engraven a <hi>Cupid,</hi> in a Throne, with this Noddy of a <hi>Fry<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ar</hi> proſtrate at his feet, with theſe Words which I have remembred,
<pb n="85" facs="tcp:171144:49"/>though they be Latin, <hi>Ave Lex, Jus, Amor.</hi> I blam'd him for this irreve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rence, which I termed Impiety, but he did but laugh at it, and ſaid he could not refuſe theſe Worſhips to thoſe who merited all manner of a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dorations; and that if I knew but how to decypher ſeven other letters, which were on the other ſide, I ſhould make many more Exclama<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions. And indeed having looked upon it again, I ſaw the ſeven fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowing Letters, <hi>A. C. D. E. D. L. G.</hi> But he would not unriddle the mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter to me, though I was very earn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eſt with him, and ſeem'd to take pett, but he perceived that I was not heartily angry with him, there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore he hug'd me once more, and we took leave of one another.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Ang.</speaker>
               <p>I am overjoyed, my Pret<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty Creature, that all things have ſucceeded ſo according to my wiſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>es; this is but a Sample of what I will do for thee. And I will pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cure
<pb n="86" facs="tcp:171144:50"/>thee the acquaintance of a <hi>Jeſuite,</hi> to whom thou wilt undoub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tedly give the Prize, and wilt own that he has got the advantage o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver all the others. But he is jea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lous of his acquaintance, even to Exceſs, tis the only fault that thou canſt find in him, otherwiſe a hand<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſome man, gallant, a florid talker and ignorant of nothing that can come to the Knowledg of a Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Agn.</speaker>
               <p>That imperfection is great enough of all conſcience, to hin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der me from having any Commu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nication with him.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Ang.</speaker>
               <p>And why ſo? Thou wilt find it a difficult matter to meet with a man who really Loves and is not jealous. I remember <hi>I</hi> was once acquainted with a <hi>Benedictin,</hi> who fancied that all the <hi>Nuns</hi> of St. <hi>Bennet</hi> could not Converſe with <hi>Fryers</hi> of another Order without in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>juſtice, and that they ſtole from him and his Fraternity all the Favours
<pb n="87" facs="tcp:171144:50"/>they beſtowed upon the <hi>Capuchins,</hi> and his reaſons were as follows. It is not to be doubted, but that men, who have devoted themſelves to Religion, are ſubject to the ſame Paſſions and Motions, with thoſe who are in the World. Where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore ſaid he, the Pounders of Orders who were very prudent Perſons, did not only raiſe Cloiſters for thoſe of their own Sex, but at the ſame time built the like for Maydens, that without having recourſe to ſtrangers, they might eaſe and com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fort one another from time to time, in the rigour of their Vows. In the beginning this was practiſed, according to the intent of the In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtitutors; by which means there a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>roſe not the leaſt ſcandal; but at pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent theſe Places ſavour too much of the General Corruption; we ſee without any trouble, the <hi>Ber<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nardin Fryer,</hi> in Conjunction with the <hi>Jacobin Nun;</hi> the <hi>Cordelier</hi> with the <hi>Benedictin Vestal;</hi> and from this
<pb n="88" facs="tcp:171144:51"/>horrible Confuſion, nothing can a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſe and proceed but Monſters.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Agn.</speaker>
               <p>That thought was pleaſant enough.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Ang.</speaker>
               <p>Alas! Cryed he, what would thoſe Holy Founders ſay at the ſight of ſo many Adulterers, if they return'd upon the Earth? How many Thunderbolts and Ana<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>themas would they hurl againſt their own Children! Would not St. <hi>Francis</hi> ſend again the <hi>Capuchins,</hi> to the <hi>Capuchineſſes,</hi> the <hi>Cordeliers</hi> to the <hi>Nuns</hi> of the ſame Order: Saint <hi>Dominick,</hi> and St. <hi>Bernard</hi> and all the reſt, would not they bring again thoſe Stragglers into the firſt way of their Rules and Conſtitu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions, that is to ſay, the <hi>Jacobins</hi> to the <hi>Jacobineſſes,</hi> the <hi>Mendicant</hi> to the <hi>Nuns</hi> of that Order? But what would become of the <hi>Jeſuites,</hi> and the <hi>Chartereux</hi> ſaid I to him, for neither St. <hi>Ignatius,</hi> nor St. <hi>Bruno</hi> drew up Rules for the <hi>Female</hi> Sex. Oh! that <hi>Spaniard,</hi> replyed he, took
<pb n="89" facs="tcp:171144:51"/>care enough for that, he did this on purpoſe that they might have oc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>caſion to forrage over all with im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>punity; beſides following his fancy which was ſomething Pederaſte, he has put 'em into imployments, wherein they find amongſt the youth moments of ſatisfaction, which they prefer before all the Divertiſements of others.</p>
               <p>As for the <hi>Chartreux,</hi> continued he, as Retreat is ſtrictly ordered them, they ſeek in themſelves the pleaſures they cannot take with o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers, and by a brisk animated Warr, they make a ſhift to ſubdue the Higheſt Temptation &amp; Inſurrecti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of the fleſh. They renew the com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bat as often as the Enemy makes any againſt them, they employ their re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiſtance in all their vigour, and call theſe ſorts of Expeditions; <hi>The Warr of Five againſt One.</hi> Well did not the Diſciple of St <hi>Bernard</hi> ſpeak ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry Learnedly?</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Agn.</speaker>
               <p>He did indeed, I ſhould
<pb n="90" facs="tcp:171144:52"/>have taken delight in hearing him.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Ang.</speaker>
               <p>There's nothing more cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain than if this was practiſed, and that if in the diſorder it ſelf, ſome rules were followed, all would go much better. It is now a year ſince that a young <hi>Nun</hi> would not have been ſo unhappy as ſhe has ſince been, if ſhe had done with the Provincial of her Order, what ſhe did with that of another. Thou haſt perhaps heard talk of Siſter <hi>Cecil,</hi> and of Father <hi>Raymond.</hi>
               </p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Agn.</speaker>
               <p>No <hi>I</hi> han't; tell me what thou knoweſt of 'em.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Ang.</speaker>
               <p>Siſter <hi>Cecil</hi> is a <hi>Nun</hi> of the Order of St. <hi>Auguſtine,</hi> and Father <hi>Raymond,</hi> was the Provincial of the <hi>Jacobins.</hi> I ſhall not tell thee after what manner he inſinuated him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf into the Breaſt of that inno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cent Creature, who had been inac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſible to all others before; But thou ſhalt only know, that he ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quired her to himſelf, that never friendſhip was more ſtrict and en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gageing,
<pb n="91" facs="tcp:171144:52"/>and they could not reſt a moment without ſeeing or receiv<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing News from one another. This Commerce was taken notice of in the Society; and the Provincial <hi>Auguſtin,</hi> who Govern'd that Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vent, having received an inckling of this matter, was ready to die for vexation; becauſe he had never been able to obtain thoſe Privacies with her, though he had uſed all man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner of means to corrupt her. She was the greateſt Beauty in that <hi>Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>naſtery.</hi> Being thus netled to the quick, he wrote to the <hi>Abbeſs,</hi> and gave her order to have an eye up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on <hi>Cecil</hi>'s Behaviour. It was an ea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſy matter for this Guardian, quick<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly to diſcover ſome extravagancies, for that the Parties were not up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on their Guard; but what they ſaw was only little wantonings; but however theſe were ſufficient to give ground and occaſion to a jea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lous man, who had the Power in his hand to miſuſe a Poor <hi>Nun.</hi>
                  <pb n="92" facs="tcp:171144:53"/>Nevertheleſs he did not entertain ſuch a deſign, but purpos'd to him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf, though making uſe of that oc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>caſion, to have from her what he had not been able to obtain before. He wrote to her himſelf, that the buſineſs might not make a noiſe, and forid her the Grate until his Arri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bval, being twenty Leagues diſtant.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Agn.</speaker>
               <p>But could any Proof be produced againſt her, that ſhe had done any notable matter?</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Ang.</speaker>
               <p>Oh! That's an eaſy buſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs to find, though there were none, when one has a deſign to deſtroy a Perſon. But all the miſchief on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly came from that ſhe was ill ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viſed. The Provincial being thus ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rived, told her, that nothing brought him thither, but the informations of her ill Conduct; that it was a ſhameful thing for ſuch a young <hi>Nun</hi> as ſhe, to abandon her ſelf to Actions, that could not be nam'd for their Infamouſneſs; and that he was very ſorry to find himſelf o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bliged,
<pb n="93" facs="tcp:171144:53"/>to inflict upon her an exem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plary puniſhment. <hi>Cecil</hi> (who was only culpable before man of ſome little wantonings, as of eying and feeling) told him that it was true, ſhe had often ſeen the Father <hi>Ray<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mond</hi> they talk'd of, but that ſhe alſo knew, that ſhe had done no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing with him, that merited any notable reprehenſion; that ſhe had forbidden him to ſee her, as ſoon as ſhe had received Orders for ſo doing; and that ſhe had thereby ſhewn, that there was nothing ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry binding in their Engagement. The Provincial to bring about his deſign, changing diſcourſe, ſpoke to her in more ſofter terms than before, and repreſented to her, that if any Mortification happened to her upon this account, ſhe her ſelf would be the cauſe of it; that ſhe might remedy the diſorder ſhe had occaſioned; and that it was a very eaſie matter for her, to parry thoſe rigorous corrections, which ſhe could
<pb n="94" facs="tcp:171144:54"/>not fail of falling under, if ſhe did not make uſe of the advantages ſhe poſſeſſed He took her at the ſame time by the hand, which he graſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ped after an Amourous manner, eying her with a ſmile, which ought to have made her underſtood the diſpoſition of her <hi>Judges</hi> Heart.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Agn.</speaker>
               <p>Did ſhe not make uſe of what ſhe had moſt engaging to free her ſelf out of the danger ſhe was in?</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Ang.</speaker>
               <p>No, ſhe did not; but took a quite contrary courſe to that ſhe ought to have followed; ſhe ima<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gin'd that it was to try her, that her <hi>Provincial</hi> ſpoke in this manner, and that his whole ſcope and de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſigne was, to Judge by her weak<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs, of what ſhe had been capable to do with the other. Upon this ill foundation, ſhe only anſwer'd him, who burnt with Love for her, by Coldneſs and words more than indifferent; which chang'd the heart of that Amourous Prieſt, who of a tender Lover became by theſe
<pb n="95" facs="tcp:171144:54"/>means an implacable Judge. Where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>upon he proceeded according to the Formes, in the information of <hi>Cecils</hi> proceſs; he received the de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſitions which jealouſie and flatte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry put into the mouth of ſeveral of her Companions, and condemned this poor Child to be whipt till Blood come, to faſt ten <hi>Frydays</hi> on <hi>Bread</hi> and <hi>Water,</hi> and to be excluded from the Parlour ſix <hi>Months:</hi> So as one may ſay, ſhe was puniſht for having been too Wiſe, and for not ſuffering her ſelf to be corrupted by the Brutality of her Superiour.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Agn.</speaker>
               <p>Good God! this ſtory moves me ſtrangely to Compaſſion; and I look upon that poor <hi>Nun,</hi> as an Innocent Victime, offered up to the rage of a Furious man, and I make no difference between her, and the Eleven thouſand Virgins.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Ang.</speaker>
               <p>Thou art in the right; for theſe are ſaid to have been ſlain, becauſe they would not ſatisfye the Paſſion of a man, and poor <hi>Cecil</hi>
                  <pb n="96" facs="tcp:171144:55"/>was only outrag'd out of the ſame Motive &amp; Reaſon. As there is no Animal in the World is more Lux<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>urious than a <hi>Monk,</hi> ſo there is none more Maligne and more Vindictive, when his Flames are deſpiſed. I have read upon this Subject a Story of a curſed <hi>Capuchin,</hi> in a Book In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tituled the <hi>Goat at Rutt.</hi> But now we talk of Books, prethee tell me what thoſe are which thou haſt re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceived during my Retreat? I ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pect to have the Reading of 'em.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Agn.</speaker>
               <p>With all my heart; ſome of them are pleaſant enough, this is the Catalogue of 'em.
<list>
                     <item>
                        <hi>Pregnant Chaſtity,</hi> a Curious <hi>No<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vel.</hi>
                     </item>
                     <item>
                        <hi>The Jeſuites Paſtime,</hi> a Piece of <hi>Ga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lantry.</hi>
                     </item>
                     <item>
                        <hi>The Priſon Enlightned,</hi> or the <hi>Open<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing of the Little-Wicket,</hi> all in <hi>Figures.</hi>
                     </item>
                     <item>
                        <hi>The Journal of the Feuillantine</hi> Nuns.</item>
                     <item>
                        <hi>The Proweſſes of the Knights of St.</hi> Lawrence.</item>
                     <item>
                        <hi>Rules and Statutes of</hi> Conny-Bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rough-Nunnery.</item>
                     <pb n="97" facs="tcp:171144:55"/>
                     <item> 
                        <hi>A Collection of Remedies againſt dangerous Swelling.</hi>
                     </item>
                     <item>Compos'd for the Conveniency of the Religious Ladies of St. <hi>George.</hi>
                     </item>
                     <item>
                        <hi>The Extrean Unction of the dy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing Virginity.</hi>
                     </item>
                     <item>
                        <hi>The Apoſtolical Orvietan</hi> Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pos'd <hi>by Four Mendicant Fryers, Expraecepto Sanctiſſimi.</hi>
                     </item>
                     <item>
                        <hi>The Monks Devotion.</hi>
                     </item>
                     <item>
                        <hi>The Abbots Pastime.</hi>
                     </item>
                     <item>
                        <hi>The Chartreux Warr.</hi>
                     </item>
                     <item>
                        <hi>The Fruits of the Unitive Life,</hi> &amp;c.</item>
                  </list> I believe I am not miſtaken, that I have not forgot one in this Liſt; I have already Read Five or Six of 'em, which have pleas'd me infinitely.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Ang.</speaker>
               <p>Certainly they have made thee a preſent of a whole Library. If the Contents be anſwerable to the Frontiſpieces, I do not doubt but that they muſt needs be very diverting: thou haſt wherewith to perfectionate thy Wit, and to ren<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der thee ſo as thou oughteſt to be,
<pb n="98" facs="tcp:171144:56"/>that is to ſay, Univerſal in all Sci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ences; for there are thoſe, who in the midſt of a great deal of light and underſtanding, do ſtill lye un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der doubts, which renders 'em ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>times uneaſy, and whoſe conſequen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces are often dangerous. <hi>I</hi> will tell thee a Story upon this Subject that happened in the <hi>Abbey</hi> at <hi>Chelles.</hi>
               </p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Agn.</speaker>
               <p>You muſt needs have won<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derful intrigues, to know all that paſs'd moſt ſecret in all the <hi>Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>naſteries.</hi>
               </p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Ang.</speaker>
               <p>Thou muſt know, that the <hi>Abbeſs</hi> of that Houſe, being of a very hot Conſtitution, was uſed to Bath every Summer for ſome weeks together. Her Bath was ſet up ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to the preſcription of Her Phyſician, who for the making it thought the better, preſcribed a particular Rule and Method to ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerve, without which it would be of no uſe. It was intirely to be prepared on the Evening, before ſhe was to go into it, and let the
<pb n="99" facs="tcp:171144:56"/>water reſt all the Night till the Morrow, and then ſhe might at certain hours go into the Bath. Sweet Scents and Eſſences were not ſpa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red, they were thrown in with pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fuſion, and all that could flatter the Lady's ſenſuality had place in his Compoſition.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Agn.</speaker>
               <p>Ah theſe Quacks and Phy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſicians by a pretended Complai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſance do thus nouriſh and inflame Peoples weakneſſes!</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Ang.</speaker>
               <p>Be it as it will; a young <hi>Nun</hi> of the Houſe called Siſter <hi>Scholaſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tica,</hi> of above Eighteen years of age, ſeeing all theſe Great preparations for my Lady <hi>Abbeſs,</hi> and perceiv<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing that the Bath was ready the Evening before, entertain'd the de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſign, (as well for eaſing her ſelf of the inconveniency of the Seaſon, as of her interiour Heat which was not very ſmall) to take hold of the Occaſion, to make tryal every Night of that ſalutary <hi>Lavabo.</hi> And indeed ſhe conſtantly went into it for eight
<pb n="100" facs="tcp:171144:57"/>days together, and found that this gave a Luſtre to her plump Bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy, and that ſhe ſlept and reſted the better for it. She went out of her Chamber about Nine a Clock, and almoſt Naked in her Smock, went to the place where all was ready; ſhe quickly got off her <hi>Petticoats</hi> and her <hi>Smock,</hi> and thus Stark Naked went ſhe in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to the <hi>Tub,</hi> where ſhe clean'd and rub'd her ſelf all over, and then af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terwards came out, as Clean, as Pure, and as Beautiful as was <hi>Eve</hi> in the Terreſtial Paradice, during the State of her Innocence.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Agn.</speaker>
               <p>Was not ſhe diſcover'd?</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Ang.</speaker>
               <p>Thoul't preſently hear the whole matter. One Night that <hi>Scholastica</hi> was Refreſhing her ſelf at the uſual Rate, one of the Old <hi>Nuns,</hi> who was not yet aſleep, ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving heard walking in the <hi>Dormi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tory,</hi> at an hour that according to Cuſtome all <hi>Nuns</hi> were to be Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tired, went out of her Chamber,
<pb n="101" facs="tcp:171144:57"/>and after having ſought to no pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe the Perſon ſhe had heard, ſhe entred into the place where the Bath ſtood, where ſhe perceived imme<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diately by the Light of the <hi>Moon,</hi> a <hi>Nun</hi> ſtark Naked, who was rub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bing her ſelf with a Napkin, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing ready to put on her Smock a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gain. The ſilly Old <hi>Dowdy</hi> think<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing it was the <hi>Abbeſs,</hi> retired in all haſt &amp; begged Pardon for her intru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion. <hi>Scholastica</hi> made her no an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwer, but could perceive that this Old <hi>Matron</hi> was miſtaken, and had taken her for another. Away went ſhe too, after having given the o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther time enough to withdraw, without intending to come thither again for fear ſhe ſhould be caught.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Agn.</speaker>
               <p>Well, but did the thing ſtop here?</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Ang.</speaker>
               <p>No, Poor <hi>Scholastica's</hi> But<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tocks would have been glad it had.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Agn.</speaker>
               <p>How! did that Pretty Crea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture come to ſuffer for it?</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Ang.</speaker>
               <p>The Venerable <hi>Matron</hi> I
<pb n="102" facs="tcp:171144:58"/>mentioned, having reflected in the Morning upon what ſhe had ſeen the Night before, thought it con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venient to go to my Lady <hi>Abbeſs,</hi> to make her her particular Excuſes for that Encounter, which ſhe might attribute to an ill Curioſity; which ſhe accordingly did, unluckily. This Extreamly Surpriz'd the <hi>Abbeſs,</hi> and made her believe, that ſhe had had only the leavings of the filth of ſome infirm <hi>Nun</hi> of her Soci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ety: ſhe ſpoke of it in the <hi>Chappel</hi> next Morning, and commanded (by Virtue of <hi>Holy Obedience</hi>) her who had put her ſelf into the Bath, to declare it. But not one of the Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pany ſpoke a Word; <hi>Scholaſtica</hi> was none of the moſt ſcrupulous, and had Wit and Senſe, wherefore ſhe held her peace. This General ſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lence put the <hi>Abbeſs</hi> into deſpair, ſhe cryed, thundred, threatn<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>d 'em all; but all to no purpoſe. At length by the Advice of a <hi>Monk,</hi> ſhe prac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiz'd a pleaſant Stratagem: She
<pb n="103" facs="tcp:171144:58"/>caus'd all her <hi>Nuns</hi> to aſſemble, and repreſented to them, that there was one among them Excomunica<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted, and in the State of Damnati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, for not having revealed what ſhe had been Commanded to de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clare by Virtue of <hi>Holy Obedience;</hi> that a Holy and Learned man had given her an infallible means to diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cover her, but that ſhe ſtill allow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed her to ſpeak the Truth, and a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>void by that means the ſevere Pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nance, which ſhe would draw up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on her ſelf, by her formal obſtinate Diſobedience.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Agn.</speaker>
               <p>Good Lord! I am terribly afraid for <hi>Scholaſtica</hi> in this per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plexity, for all the Counſel of <hi>Monks</hi> are always pernicious.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Ang</speaker>
               <p>My Lady <hi>Abbeſs</hi> ſeeing that this laſt Conſtraint had been with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out effect, ſhe followed the Ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vice that had been given her. She caus'd a Table in a Room to be cover'd with a <hi>Coffin-Pall,</hi> &amp; ſet in the midſt the Cup of the Sacriſtie.
<pb n="104" facs="tcp:171144:59"/>This being ſo diſpos'd, ſhe com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>manded all her Veſtals to enter after one another into that Room, and to touch with their right hand the Foot of that Sacred Cup, (theſe were the Terms ſhe uſed) that was ſet upon the Table, that by this means ſhe ſhould know, who it was that ſo obſtinately concealed this wicked Fact ſo long, becauſe that ſhe would no ſooner have put her fingers upon that Sacred Cup, than that the Table would fall upon the floor, and diſcover by a ſecret Ver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tue from above, ſhe who ſhould be Culpable. This was done about Nine a Clock at Night, and in the dark: whereupon they all entred in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to the Room, and toucht the Foot of the Cup with their hands. <hi>Scho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>laſtica</hi> was the only Perſon who durſt not do it, for fear of being diſcovered, and only toucht the Carpet. After which ſhe retired with the reſt into another Room, which was alſo without Light, from
<pb n="105" facs="tcp:171144:59"/>whence the <hi>Abbeſs</hi> made them come to her one after the other, when all the Ceremonies were over. Now it is obſervable, that ſhe had blacked the foot of the Cup with Oyl and Soot, ſo as it was impoſſible to touch it, without bearing away the marks of it. Thus having lighted a Candle in the Room ſhe was in, ſhe viewed the hands of all thoſe <hi>Nuns,</hi> and found they had all toucht the Cup, except <hi>Scholaſtica</hi> who had no black upon her fingers, like the reſt of Her Society. This made her judge, that it muſt be ſhe who had committed the fault. This poor innocent Creature, ſeeing her ſelf thus trappan'd by this Trick and Artifice, had recourſe to tears and excuſes, and came off for a couple of Diſciplines, which ſhe received be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore all the Company. Well! this was only that outſide of Religion, which was impiouſly made uſe of, which made her afraid; and if ſhe had made the leaſt reflection upon
<pb n="106" facs="tcp:171144:60"/>the impoſſibility there was, of diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>covering her by ſo ridiculous an Artifice, ſhe would not have been found out.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Agn.</speaker>
               <p>That's right; but the <hi>Abbeſs</hi> ought to have pardoned her, upon the account of her Beauty and her Youth.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Ang.</speaker>
               <p>She might ſo, but ſhe did not; nay, and I have heard ſay, that the firſt Diſcipline, which ſhe or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dered her, laſted for above a quar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter of an hour; judge then of the condition the poor Buttocks of that pretty Creature muſt needs be in.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Agn.</speaker>
               <p>They were undoubtedly much like mine when I ſhewed 'em thee: If it lay in my Power I would condemn that Curſed Counſel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lour of the <hi>Abbeſs</hi> to be a per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>petual Gally Slave; and if the ſame buſineſs had happened to me, I would have laid ſo many ſnares for that <hi>Monk,</hi> by the means of ſome friends abroad, that I would have made him repent his Stratagem.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <pb n="107" facs="tcp:171144:60"/>
               <speaker>Ang.</speaker>
               <p>Doſt thou think, that if he had in the leaſt ſuſpected this puniſhment would have fallen upon <hi>Scholastica,</hi> he would have had a hand in it? No; he i<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>magin'd as well as the <hi>Abbeſs,</hi> that it was ſome Old or ſome Infirm Creature that had been ſurprized, and it is that that turn'd the La<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy <hi>Abbeſſes</hi> Stomach, for having, as ſhe fancied, waſh'd her ſelf in the filthy leavings of ſuch Perſons.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Agn.</speaker>
               <p>For my part I believe ſhe was more at eaſe, when ſhe knew it was <hi>Scholaſtica,</hi> who had been dab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bling in the Bath; for people are not diſguſted with a young neat and handſome Girl, as thou haſt repreſented her to me. The Penance ſhe received puts me in mind of that of <hi>Virginia,</hi> and of the Chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren of the <hi>Jeſuites</hi> four-ſquare-Cap.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Ang.</speaker>
               <p>Stay; Ile ſhew you two of 'em I have in my Box, one from Father <hi>Raucourt,</hi> the other from <hi>Virginia;</hi> here read this firſt.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <pb n="108" facs="tcp:171144:61"/>
               <speaker>Agn.</speaker>
               <p>This is almoſt like a wo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mans hand, it is ſo ſcrawl'd and ſo careleſsly written.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Ah God! My Dear Child, now do I begin to be tyred with this commerce of Letters! It does but the more Aug<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment my Flames, and not eaſe 'em in the least. It tells me that</hi> Virgi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nia <hi>has a kindneſs for me, but lets me know at the ſame time, that it is impoſſible for me to enjoy her. Alas! what ſtrange motions does this mix<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture of ſweetneſs and bitterneſs cauſe in ſuch a heart as mine! I had heard ſay, that Love ſometimes inſpires thoſe with Wit who were unprovided of it, but I find in my ſelf a quite contrary effect; and I may truly ſay, that it takes from me what it doth preſent to others; ſeveral take notice of this change, but they are ignorant of the cauſe of it. I yeſterday Preached at the Convent of the</hi> Nuns, <hi>of the Viſitation, never was I more animated, &amp; inſpired; I ought Conformably to my Subject have entertain'd the Company with Morti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fication
<pb n="109" facs="tcp:171144:61"/>and Penance; But my whole Sermon and Diſcourſe was made up of affections, and tenderneſſes, and ſailleys and tranſports. It is you,</hi> Virginia, <hi>who cauſes all this diſorder; wherefore take compaſſion of the confuſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on I am in, and endeavour betimes to find the means of bringing me back to my right Senſes.</hi>
               </p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Ang.</speaker>
               <p>Well <hi>Agnes,</hi> what doſt thou ſay of this Child got in haſt?</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Agn.</speaker>
               <p>I find it worthy of its Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, and capable all naked as it is of Dreſs and Ornament, not only of keeping to it ſelf a heart that it poſſeſſes, but even of exciting there new motions.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Ang.</speaker>
               <p>Thou art in the right; for in ſome the moſt careleſs ſtile is al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ways the moſt perſwaſive; and of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tentimes all the Eloquence of an Oratour cannot produce thoſe ſoft Tranſports in a Breaſt, as are on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly the effects of a leſs lofty term, but more expreſſive. This is a Truth I can give Teſtimony of, ſince I
<pb n="110" facs="tcp:171144:62"/>have tryed it ſeveral times in my ſelf. But let us ſee a little, if <hi>Vir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ginia</hi> expreſſes her ſelf ſo well as her Lover.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Agn.</speaker>
               <p>Give me the Letter that I may read it.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Ang.</speaker>
               <p>There take it, tis rather a Note than a Letter, for its but five or ſix Lines in all.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Agn.</speaker>
               <p>Her hand is little different from mine.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Ah! how cunning are you in your words, and you know to perfection the art of diſturbing the little Repoſe a poor innocent Creature who lov's you has left? can you with reaſon ask me, if I think on you? Alas, my Dear, con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſult but with your own ſelf, and be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lieve that we cannot both be anima<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted with one and the ſame Paſſion, without undergoing the like and e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>qual torments.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Adieu! be mindful of the breaking of our Chaines; Love renders me Capa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pable of any enterprize. Ah! how much weakneſs does it cauſe in me!</hi>
               </p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <pb n="111" facs="tcp:171144:62"/>
               <speaker>Ang.</speaker>
               <p>In good earneſt, Doſt thou not think-this Note more tender than the Letter?</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Agn.</speaker>
               <p>Yes indeed. We may ſay it is all Heart, and that two or three Periods expreſs as much the diſpoſition of the Soul of a Lover, as would do two Pages of a Ro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mance. But I do not ſee that it is an anſwer to that we have read from Father <hi>Raucourt.</hi>
               </p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Ang.</speaker>
               <p>No, 'tis not, 'tis to an other which was not ſent me.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Agn.</speaker>
               <p>I pitty the misfortunes of thoſe two Lovers; eſpecially I bear an extream Compaſſion to the trou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bles of <hi>Virginia,</hi> for undoubtedly ſhe ſpends her time at preſent in a great deal of anxiety and affliction, and leads a very wretched tedious life.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Ang.</speaker>
               <p>If ſhe had not kept the Let<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters and Notes that had been ſent to her, ſhe would not have been ſo unhappy; for then they would not have diſcovered the Deſign ſhe had,
<pb n="112" facs="tcp:171144:63"/>of making her eſcape out of the Monaſtery.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Agn.</speaker>
               <p>Then it is undoubtedly that ſhe means, when ſhe ſayes in Her Letter, <hi>Think of the rupture of our Chains.</hi> I ſhould not have hit of the right ſence of theſe words; Alas! poor Creature, how unhap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>py had ſhe been, had ſhe commit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted that egregious miſtake: Alack<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>aday, Alackaday! What is not Love capable of doing, when it meets with oppoſition.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Ang.</speaker>
               <p>As ſoon as the Rector of the <hi>Jeſuites</hi> had learnt what paſſed, by the Letter he found in the Bon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>net, he gave notice thereof to the <hi>Abbeſs,</hi> who went immediately with Her Aſſiſtance to ſearch <hi>Vir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ginia</hi>'s Chamber, where ſhe found in her Box an infinite Number of Letters and other trifles, which diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>covered to her the truth of what ſhe could not have believed, if ſhe had not ſeen it. As ſhe highly loved <hi>Virginia,</hi> ſhe onely ſhew'd
<pb n="113" facs="tcp:171144:63"/>in theſe proceedings, what ſhe could not well conceal, and moderated the puniſhment which the Conſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tutions do preſcribe.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Agn.</speaker>
               <p>The <hi>Jeſuite</hi> was more hap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>py ſince he came off onely for Changing his Province.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Ang.</speaker>
               <p>Phoogh! You're miſtaken, this ſtorm did not blow over ſo eaſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly as thou imagineſt. He is at preſent out of Society. Thou muſt know that as in that Society all is hing'd and eſtabliſhed upon Eſteem and Reputation, it is im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſſible for a man of honour to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>main in it, after he has loſt by ſome accident, thoſe two things which ſo agreably flatter the Ambition of mankind. Father <hi>Raucourt</hi> ſeeing himſelf thus fallen, by the misfor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tune I told thee, from that degree of Glory, which he had acquired by his Merits, and wherein he had alwayes maintained himſelf by his Prudence, ſet little value upon the Indulgence which his Superiours
<pb n="114" facs="tcp:171144:64"/>offered him, and thought onely of abandoning them; which he did a while agoe, and retired into <hi>England.</hi>
               </p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Agn.</speaker>
               <p>What can a man do in a forreign Country, who has no other fortune than knowledge, nor other Eſtate than Philoſophy.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Ang.</speaker>
               <p>What can he do? Why he can render himſelf more uſeful to the Common-Wealth, than all the Artificers who compoſe it: He may by his writings give vigour to Laws the moſt oppoſite to the Inclination of the people; he may carry the Glory of a Nation into places the moſt remote: In ſhort, there are very few Employments, but which he can worthily acquit himſelf of, and from which the State may draw conſiderable Advanta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ges. As what I ſay is not void of Reaſon, ſo neither is it without ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ample; and I have learnt from a <hi>Dominican,</hi> that a Male-content of their Order was at the Court of
<pb n="115" facs="tcp:171144:64"/>that Kingdom, whither <hi>Raucourt</hi> made his Retreat, and that he made a very fine Figure there, in the quality of a Reſident or Envoy of a <hi>German Prince.</hi>
               </p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Agn.</speaker>
               <p>Without doubt he would have conducted <hi>Virginia</hi> into that Countrey, if they had brought a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bout their deſigns. Alas! there would be but few recluſed of ei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther Sex, if thoſe who go into <hi>Cloy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sters</hi> had but time given them to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>flect upon the Advantages of Civil Liberty, and upon the ill Conſequences of a Fatal En<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gagement.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Ang</speaker>
               <p>Why doſt thou talk at this rate? Cannot we enjoy as perfect Pleaſures within the compaſs of our walls, as thoſe do who are abroad? The Obſtacles that oppoſe them, do but ſerve to give 'em the better taſte and reliſh, when that after ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving cunningly and dextrouſly ſur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mounted 'em, we poſſeſs what we have deſired. It would be both
<pb n="116" facs="tcp:171144:65"/>maligne and ungrateful, to cenſure the Divertizements both of <hi>Monks</hi> and <hi>Nuns;</hi> for I ſhould ask thoſe people, is it not true, that Conti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nency is a gift of God, which he gratifies whom he pleaſes with, and which he only beſtows upon thoſe whom he thinks fitting to Honour! This being ſuppoſed, he will only require an account of that Preſent from thoſe to whom he gave it.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Agn.</speaker>
               <p>I do well enough under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtand the ſtrength of that reaſon, but one might ſay that the Vows by which we ſolemnly engage our ſelves, do render us reſponſible be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore him.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Ang.</speaker>
               <p>And doſt thou not perceive, that thoſe Vows which thou ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>keſt in the hands of men, are on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly Songs? Canſt thou with reaſon oblige thy ſelf to give what thou haſt not? And what thou canſt not have, unleſs it pleaſes him to whom thou offereſt it, to grant it thee?
<pb n="117" facs="tcp:171144:65"/>Judge from hence of the Nature of our engagements; and if to the ri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gour we are held according to God, to the effect of our promiſes; ſince that they contain in 'em a moral impoſſibility, thou haſt no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing to ſay to deſtroy this ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gument.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Agn.</speaker>
               <p>'Tis true, I have not, and this is what ought to ſet our minds at reſt?</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Ang.</speaker>
               <p>For my part I may ſay, that nothing troubles me, I ſpend my time in an Equallity of mind, which renders me inſenſible to the Tor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments which weary and fatigue o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers. I ſee all, hear all, but few things are capable of moveing me; and if my Repoſe were not trou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bled by ſome Corporal Indiſpoſiti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, there is not a Perſon could Live with more Tranquility than I do.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Agn.</speaker>
               <p>But in a Conduct ſo oppo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſite to that of other Cloiſters, What do you think of the diſpoſition of
<pb n="118" facs="tcp:171144:66"/>their Souls, and thoſe Actions which are followed as they Preach, with ſo many merits, do not they tempt by the hopes they propoſe? They might tell us, that Libertiniſm is often capable to furniſh us with Reaſons for our own ruine. For what is more Holy than the Meditation of Celeſtial things, wherein they imploy themſelves? What is more Laudible and Praiſe-worthy than that great Piety which they put in practice, and the faſtings and auſterities wherewith they mor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tifie themſelves, can they paſs under the Notion of Fruitleſs Works?</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Ang.</speaker>
               <p>Ah! my poor Child, how weak are all theſe obligations. Thou muſt know, that there is a great deal of difference between Licenciouſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs &amp; Liberty; I often in my acti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons hold my ſelf upon the rim of the latter, but now fall into the diſorder of the former. If I do not give bounds to my joy and to
<pb n="119" facs="tcp:171144:66"/>my pleaſures, it is becauſe they are innocent, and that they never wound by their exceſs the things for which I ought to have a Ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neration. But give me leave to tell thee what I think of thoſe Melancholly Fools, with whoſe man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ners thou art charmed; doſt thou know that what thou calleſt Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>templation of things Divine, is on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly at the bottom a ſordid Lazi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs incapable of all Action? That the Motions of that Heroick Piety which thou ſo much extolleſt, do only proceed from the diſorder of a crack'd Brain; and that to find out the cauſe that makes them tear themſelves like diſtracted people, you muſt ſeek it in the va<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pours of a Black humour, or in the weakneſs of their Pericra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nium?</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Agn.</speaker>
               <p>I take ſo much delight in hearing thy Reaſons, that I propo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed to thee all on purpoſe as a dif<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ficulty which did not make me ſuf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fer
<pb n="120" facs="tcp:171144:67"/>the leaſt doubt; but I hear the Bell that calls us!</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Ang.</speaker>
               <p>It is to go to the Refec<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tory, after Dinner we will conti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nue our Conferences.</p>
            </sp>
            <trailer>The End of the Second Dialogue.</trailer>
         </div>
         <div n="3" type="dialogue">
            <pb n="121" facs="tcp:171144:67"/>
            <head>
               <hi>Venus</hi> in the <hi>Cloister,</hi> OR THE <hi>Nun</hi> in Her <hi>Smock.</hi>
            </head>
            <head type="sub">Third <hi>Dialogue.</hi>
            </head>
            <stage>Siſter <hi>Agnes,</hi> Siſter <hi>Angelica.</hi>
            </stage>
            <sp>
               <speaker>AGnes,</speaker>
               <p>Ah how Grateful and Pleaſant is the Beauty of this Day! It Revives all my Spi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rits. Let us both retire into that <hi>Alley,</hi> that ſo we may get rid of the Company of others.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Angelica,</speaker>
               <p>We cannot find a more convenient place in all the Garden for our Walk, for the Trees which environ us, give us as much ſhade
<pb n="122" facs="tcp:171144:68"/>as is neceſſary, to hinder our being expos'd to the heat of the Sun.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Agn.</speaker>
               <p>True; but it is to be feared that my Lady <hi>Abbeſs</hi> will come to recreate her ſelf here, for this is the place ſhe moſt commonly chooſes to take the Air in after meals.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Ang.</speaker>
               <p>Be not you afraid of her coming to diſturb us here, ſhe is indiſpos'd at preſent, and if thou kneweſt but the cauſe of her indiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſition, thou wouldeſt laugh hearti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Agn.</speaker>
               <p>Why ſhe was well enough yeſterday?</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Ang</speaker>
               <p>Shee was ſo, the Diſaſter only befel her this night, and thou muſt needs have ſlept very ſound<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, if thou didſt not perceive that, by her ſhrikes and bawlings out, ſhe frighted and alarum'd all the Dormitory. I intended to have made it part of our Diverſion when I came unto thee this morning; but inſenſibly our Converſation devia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted upon other ſubjects.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <pb n="123" facs="tcp:171144:68"/>
               <speaker>Agn.</speaker>
               <p>The truth is, I hear no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing but what's publick.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Ang.</speaker>
               <p>You know that one of my Ladyes Principal Pleaſures conſiſts in nouriſhing all ſorts of Animals, and that ſhe does not content her ſelf with enjoying an infinite num<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber of Birds, ſhe has likewiſe ren<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dered tame &amp; Domeſtick, even <hi>Tor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>toiſes</hi> and <hi>Fiſh.</hi> As ſhe makes no ſecret of this folly, and that ſhe calls this Amuſement, <hi>The charms of a Solitary Life;</hi> they all endea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vour to Contribute to her Divertize<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, by making her preſents ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>times of one Creature, ſometimes of another. The <hi>Abbot</hi> of St. <hi>Vallery</hi> having heard that she had rendred, (as he had been given to under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtand) even <hi>Carps</hi> and <hi>Pikes,</hi> tame and familiar; he ſent her four days ago two live <hi>Mackerells,</hi> two <hi>Sea Crabs,</hi> likewiſe living. After having caus'd the wings of thoſe Demy-Ducks to be cut, ſhe put them in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to the Pond, reſolved to make it
<pb n="124" facs="tcp:171144:69"/>her whole buſineſs to look after the Craw-Fiſh; for which reaſon ſhe caus'd a little Trough to be brought into her Chamber, which ſhe had filled with water, and where ſhe put thoſe <hi>Lobſters,</hi> (ſo are thoſe <hi>A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nimals</hi> called). It is hardly to be ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſſed what pains ſhe took for their preſervation, even to the caſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing them Sweet-meats and Sugar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plums; in ſhort, ſhe would only feed 'em with the moſt delicate meats and food.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Agn.</speaker>
               <p>Thoſe ſort of paſtimes are innocent and excuſable in youth.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Ang.</speaker>
               <p>Yeſterday Evening, by ill luck, Siſter <hi>Olinda,</hi> who had order to change the water every day in the Trough for the refreſhment of the Fiſh, forgot to do it, which was the cauſe of all this diſorder. You muſt know that the laſt night having been very hot, one of theſe <hi>Lobſters,</hi> finding himſelf incommoded by the heat it felt, went out of the Trough, and trail'd along the Cham<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber,
<pb n="125" facs="tcp:171144:69"/>untill that ſeeing it ſelf with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out eaſe, it ſought after the wa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter it had left, as its moſt Natural Element. But as it was much more eaſy for it to deſcend than to mount, it was conſtrain'd to have recourſe to the water of my Ladyes Chamber-Pot, where without examining whether it was freſh or ſalt it po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſted it ſelf. Some time after our <hi>Ab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>beſs</hi> had occaſion to piſs, and half aſleep, and without going out of the Bed, ſhe took her Urinal; but alas! ſhe had like to have been frighted to death, this <hi>Crah-Fiſh</hi> finding it ſelf watered with ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing too warm a ſhower, lanched forth towards the place from whence it ſeem'd to come, and ſeiz'd it ſo hard with one of its paws, that take my word it has left marks there for above this week.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Agn.</speaker>
               <p>Ha, ha, ha, This, this in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deed is a pleaſant Adventure!</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Ang.</speaker>
               <p>At the very ſame mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment ſhe gave a skrich that awa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kened
<pb n="126" facs="tcp:171144:70"/>all her neighbours, flung the <hi>Looking-glaſs</hi> upon the floor, and get<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing up in a terrible fright, called people to her help. In the mean while this <hi>Animall,</hi> that had never met with ſo delicate and ſo reliſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing a bit, let not go its hold. The Mother <hi>Aſſiſtant,</hi> and Siſter <hi>Corne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lia,</hi> were the ſooneſt up; <hi>Cornelia</hi> had much ado to forbear laughing at the ſight of ſuch a ſcene, but check'd her ſelf however the beſt ſhe was able. But the Mother <hi>Aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiſtant</hi> being dim-ſighted, put on her <hi>Spectacles</hi> to ſee what was the matter, and peering too nigh, the <hi>Crab</hi> caught hold of her noſe with the other Claw; this added to <hi>Cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nelias</hi>'s Diverſion, who was for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ced to cut off the Claws of that Sacrilegious Creature, which till then did not abandon its prey. The Mother <hi>Aſſiſt<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>nt</hi> withdrew to her own Room, very much concerned at the outrage done to her Reve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rend Noſe; and Siſter <hi>Cornelia,</hi> who
<pb n="127" facs="tcp:171144:70"/>is my Lady <hi>Abbeſs</hi>'s Confident, ſpent the reſt of the Night with her to comfort her in this diſtreſs. This is the cauſe of our <hi>Abbeſſes</hi> indiſpo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſition, which will apparently hin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der her from interrupting our con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ferences.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Agn.</speaker>
               <p>Ah Lord! I ſhould not dare to appear if ſuch an accident had happened to me, and that it was come to other peoples know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledg.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Ang.</speaker>
               <p>Truly a mighty buſineſs to be aſhamed of, ſhe let nothing be ſeen but what ſhe had often ſhown to others, and the Knights of the Order have plac'd their hands ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veral times where the <hi>Crab</hi> placed his paw.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Agn.</speaker>
               <p>But which of all her Knights is her greateſt Darling.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Ang.</speaker>
               <p>I know not well which is, but this I know that a <hi>Jeſuite</hi> vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſits her often, and that he has had privacies with her, that give us to underſtand he is one of the <hi>Blew-Ribbons.</hi>
                  <pb n="128" facs="tcp:171144:71"/>I perceived her one day with him in a very ſervent Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>munication; &amp; at another time that she went out with the ſame Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon, I found in the Parlour ſhe went out of, a Napkin wet in certain places with a certain viſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cous Liquor; ſhe had let it fall neer the window; I do not ſpeak of this Rencounter, I only obſerved that the loſs made her ſomewhat unea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſy.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Agn.</speaker>
               <p>What needed ſhee to fear, the Biſhop on whom ſhe depends, is wholly at her Diſcretion, in the viſit he has made of this <hi>Monaſte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry,</hi> he had ordered nothing but what ſhe had before preſcribed to him.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Ang.</speaker>
               <p>Right, Shee is Miſtreſs of all, and the Directours and Confeſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſors are only received and changed by her Order.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Agn.</speaker>
               <p>Ah! I could wiſh with all my heart, that our Common Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſor whom we have at preſent,
<pb n="129" facs="tcp:171144:71"/>did but diſpleaſe her, as much as he does me; what ſayeſt thou to it?</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Ang.</speaker>
               <p>The truth, is he is very au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtere, and is capable of putting thoſe to a great deal of trouble who knew not how to behave them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves; but to ſuch as you and I, it ought to be indifferent to us whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther it be he, or a leſs rigorous Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon who hears us.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Agn.</speaker>
               <p>For my part, I cannot con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſs the leaſt tyny ſin, but that he falls into a Paſſion. For a thought I accuſed my ſelf of, he ordered me terrible Mortifications and Pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nances, and will make me faſt two days for the leaſt motion of the Fleſh that I ſhall confeſs to him. Beſides, I know not what moſt com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monly to Entertain him with, for fear of telling him ſomething that ſhould diſpleaſe him. And I can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not conceive what courſe thou ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>keſt, thou who keepeſt him ſo long?</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <pb n="130" facs="tcp:171144:72"/>
               <speaker>Ang.</speaker>
               <p>And doſt thou believe me ſo ſilly as to declare to him the ſecret of my heart; for from that, as I conceive him altogether rigid, I only tell him ſuch things as there is no hold to be laid on; he cannot conclude from all that he hears from me, but that I am a Mai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>den of Prayer and Contemplation, who is not acquainted with all the Motions of a Corrupted Nature, which makes him he dares not queſtion me upon that matter; the ſevereſt Penance I have received, is <hi>Five Pater Noſters,</hi> and the <hi>Li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tanies.</hi>
               </p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Agn.</speaker>
               <p>But what doſt thou ſay to him then, for only having broke ſilence, or droll'd upon a Perſon of the Community, (which is nothing) he will Schooll me for a quarter of an hour</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Ang.</speaker>
               <p>All theſe faults being de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſigned in particular, with their Cir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cumſtances, of ſmall, become ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>times more Conſiderable; and this
<pb n="131" facs="tcp:171144:72"/>is what renders thee ſubject to his Reprehenſion. But ſee the courſe I take by giving Ear to my laſt Confeſſion. After having moſt humbly begg'd his Bleſſing, with my eyes down, my hands lifted up, and my Body bending: I began in this manner.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>My Father, I am the greatest Sin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner on the Earth, and the weakeſt of all Creatures, I almost ever fall into the ſame faults.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>I accuſe my ſelf of having trou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bled the Tranquility of my ſoul, with Univerſal Divagations, which have put my Breaſt in diſorder.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Of not having had ſufficient Recol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lection of mind, and of having ſpent too much time in external Occupati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Of having dwelt too long upon the Opperations of the underſtanding, ſpend<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing therein the moſt of my Prayers to the prejudice of my will, which re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>main'd by that means dry and bar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ren.</hi>
               </p>
               <pb n="132" facs="tcp:171144:73"/>
               <p> 
                  <hi>Of having at another time ſuffer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed my ſelf to be engag'd in Affecti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, and expoſed thereby to trouble<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſome Diſtractions, and to a Lazyneſs of Spirit, contrary to the methodicall perfection of the Contemplative.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Of having kept too much in me, too much of what is belonging to me, without diſengaging my heart from all Created things, by a generous Act of ſuppreſſion of ſelf Love, Interests, De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſires and Wills, and of my ſelf.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Of having made an offering of my heart without having first of all Tran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quillized and Pacified it, and freed it from the trouble of the too unru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly Paſſions and diſorderly affections.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Of having ſuffered my ſelf to be led away by the inclinations of the Old man, and by the proneneſs of an un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>repaired Nature, inſtead of making a Divorce from all, for the gaining all.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Of not having been carefull to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>new my ſelf by a review of my ſelf, in my ſelf, and of making the Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>paration
<pb n="133" facs="tcp:171144:73"/>in me of what was decay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed,</hi> &amp;c.</p>
               <p>Well <hi>Agnes,</hi> Thou mayeſt judge of the whole piece by this Sam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple. This is not the third part of my Confeſſion, but the reſt ren<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ders me no more Criminal than this beginning.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Agn.</speaker>
               <p>The truth is, that I ſhould be very much puzzled, were I to order Penances to Sins ſo ingeniouſly laid open; and yet this is the on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly way to deceive the Curioſity of young Directours, and avoid the Reprimands of the Old.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Ang.</speaker>
               <p>The Latter are commonly the leaſt tractable; for I have ſeen but few Faſts, ſince I have been in the Society, but what have been pretty indulgent.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Agn.</speaker>
               <p>The truth is, that they have not all the ſame rigours, Witneſs him who Imprinted Devotion ſo deep in the Soul of two of our Siſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters, that they found themſelves very much incommoded Nine Months afterwards.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <pb n="134" facs="tcp:171144:74"/>
               <speaker>Ang.</speaker>
               <p>Good Lord! 'Tis well they had ſo much Wit and Cunning, to conceal it as they did, and to hin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der this job from being blab'd a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>broad. It came not ſo much as to the knowledg of the Biſhop him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf, but when there could no lon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger any proof be made thereof. It puts me in mind of an <hi>Italian-Jeſuite,</hi> who one day Confeſſing a young <hi>French</hi> Gentleman, who had learnt the Language of the Country, gave an Exclamation without thinking of it, which made known his weakneſs. The Peni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tent accus'd himſelf of having ſpent the night with a young Lady of of one of the Principal Families of <hi>Rome,</hi> and of having enjoyed her according to his deſire; The Good Father looking very wiſhfully &amp; at<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tentively on the Perſon who ſpoke to him, being a handſome youth &amp; well made, forgot himſelf ſo far as to the Office he performed, and imagining himſelf to be in a free Converſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion,
<pb n="135" facs="tcp:171144:74"/>ſo tranſported was he, he ask'd the young Spark, if ſhe was Beautifull, what Age ſhe was of, and how many times he had done the job with her? The <hi>French</hi> man making his anſwer, that he had found her a perfect, exquiſite Beau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty, that ſhe was but Eighteen years Old, and that he had done it three times. <hi>Ah qual guſto Sig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nior,</hi> Cryed he then pretty loud; that's to ſay, Ah the delight and pleaſure of the enjoyment of ſuch a Creature!</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Agn.</speaker>
               <p>This Sailly was not unplea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſant, and very capable of Excit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing the heat of a Penitent to the repentance of ſuch a fault.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Ang.</speaker>
               <p>What wouldſt thou have, they are men as well as others: and I have heard one of my friends ſay, who was in thoſe ſort of Em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ployments, that often a Confeſſor would not expoſe himſelf ſo much by going to a Bawdy-Houſe, were it not for what the devout whiſper in his Ear.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <pb n="136" facs="tcp:171144:75"/>
               <speaker>Agn.</speaker>
               <p>For my part, I ſhould find methinks that Occupation pretty Diverting, provided I was allowed to make choice of my Penitent: I ſhould take pleaſure in hearing 'em, and my imagination would be notably tickled by the account they ſhould give me of their fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lies. Which would not be with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out a great deal of pleaſure on my Part.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Ang.</speaker>
               <p>Alas my Child! Knoweſt thou what thou askeſt? if a Devout Woman affords a little pleaſure to a Confeſſor by the ingenious ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>count ſhe gives of her weakneſſes, there are a thouſand who weary them by their repetitions, who tire them out with their ſcruples; and when they would with more eaſe free themſelves out of an <hi>Abbyſs</hi> than from their doubts. Siſter <hi>Doſithea</hi> has for above three years almoſt, ſolely taken up the Common Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rectour of the Houſe by her Queſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions. It was to no purpoſe for
<pb n="137" facs="tcp:171144:75"/>him to repreſent to her, that thoſe curious Niceties wherewith ſhe tor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tured her Conſcience, never think<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing ſhe had taken care enough to examine her ſelf, were not only uſeleſs but likewiſe vicious and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trary to perfection; he could do no good with her, and was Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrain'd to abandon her to her ſelf, and leave her in her errour.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Agn.</speaker>
               <p>Methinks however, that ſhe is at preſent more reaſonable; and I remember that once we were ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lidged to lye both together, while that our <hi>Dormitory</hi> was ſetting up; ſhe kept me in diſcourſe, but in ſuch diſcourſe as was not only far from any ſcruple, but likewiſe which I found at that time ſomewhat too free and libertine. Beſides a thou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſand wantonings to which ſhe ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cited me, by the Relation of an hundred Stories, the moſt Smutty and Laſcivious imaginable.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Ang.</speaker>
               <p>I perceive thou knoweſt not how ſhe was freed out of the
<pb n="138" facs="tcp:171144:76"/>errour Superſtition had plung'd her ſo deep in: her Confeſſor had no ſhare in her delivery; we may ſay that it is Devotion it ſelf that has produced this change and that of a Maiden extreamly Scrupulous, it has made a Religious altogether reaſonable. I am content to tell all I know of this matter, from her own mouth.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Agn.</speaker>
               <p>I do not well conceive this, for to ſay that Devotion can rid a perſon of her Scruples, is to ſay, that a blind man is capable of free<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing another from a Precipice.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Ang.</speaker>
               <p>Hear me but, and thou wilt find I have urg'd nothing but what is true. Siſter <hi>Doſithea</hi> as you may perceive by her eyes, is na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turally of the moſt tendereſt a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>morous Complexion imaginable; this poor Creature at her entrance into Religion, fell into the hands of an old Director ſuperlatively igno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rant, and ſo much the more an E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nemy of Nature, as that his Age
<pb n="139" facs="tcp:171144:76"/>rendred him uncapable of all the plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſures it propoſes. Thus finding that the inclination of his Penitent was car<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nally given, and that the failing, and weakneſſes ſhe accuſed herſelf of every day, were a certain ſign of it; He thought it was his duty to reform that Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture which he called Corrupted, and that it was allowed him to erect himſelf into a ſecond Rapairer. To bring this deſign about, he caſt into her mind all the Seeds of Scruples, of doubts, of tor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments, and pains of Conſcience he could bethink himſelf of. He did it with ſo much the more ſucceſs, as that he found a diſpoſition in her to 'em, and that the ingenuous Confeſſions he had often heard from this innocent Creature, made him know the extream tenderneſs ſhe had in what concerned her Salvation.</p>
               <p>Whereupon he gave her a deſcription of the way to Heaven in ſuch courſe co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lours, that they would have been capa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble of diſcouraging and diſguſting from the perſuit of it, a Perſon leſs zealous, and leſs fervent than Siſter <hi>Doſithea.</hi> He only ſpoke to her of the Deſtruction of that Body, which oppoſed it ſelf to the enjoyment of the Spirit, and the hor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rible penances wherewith he loaded her
<pb n="140" facs="tcp:171144:77"/>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 span">
                     <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                  </gap> ſaid, means abſolutely neceſſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap> 
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 span">
                     <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                  </gap> which it was impoſſible for <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 span">
                     <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                  </gap> arrive at that Celeſtiall <hi>Jeruſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="3 letters">
                        <desc>•••</desc>
                     </gap>
                  </hi> 
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 span">
                     <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                  </gap>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 span">
                     <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                  </gap> not being capable to defend <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 span">
                     <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                  </gap> againſt theſe arguments, ſuffer'd <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 span">
                     <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                  </gap> to be led away blindly by the <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 span">
                     <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                  </gap> 
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>eet Devotion, with which ſhe was <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> 
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>ated: The plain practice of God's <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="3 letters">
                     <desc>•••</desc>
                  </gap>andments, was no longer thought <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 span">
                     <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                  </gap> to be of any great conſideration <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 span">
                     <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                  </gap> him, they were to be accompa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap> 
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 span">
                     <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                  </gap> with works of ſupererrogation, and <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 span">
                     <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                  </gap> 
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ith all this Clutter, ſhe was ſtill <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 span">
                     <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                  </gap> 
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ontinual fear of the paines of a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap> 
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 span">
                     <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                  </gap> World, with which ſhe was ſo <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 span">
                     <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                  </gap> 
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>reatned. As it is impoſſible here <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 span">
                     <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                  </gap> deſtroy in us what we call Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap> 
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 span">
                     <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                  </gap>, ſhe was never in peace with <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 span">
                     <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                  </gap> it was a perpetual War which <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 span">
                     <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                  </gap> prudently made upon her poor <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 span">
                     <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                  </gap> and the ſierce Conflicts ſhe in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap> 
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 span">
                     <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                  </gap> upon it, were rarely followed with <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 span">
                     <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                  </gap> 
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>rt Ceſſation.</p>
               <p>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 span">
                     <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                  </gap> Alas! poor Creature, I pitty <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 span">
                     <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                  </gap> how ſtrangely ſhould. I have <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 span">
                     <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                  </gap> 
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>ved with Compaſſion, had I ſeen <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 span">
                     <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                  </gap> 
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>hat errour.</p>
               <p>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 span">
                     <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                  </gap> As her amourous diſpoſition cau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap> 
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="3 letters">
                     <desc>•••</desc>
                  </gap>er, her greateſt failings, She
<pb n="141" facs="tcp:171144:77"/>neglected nothing of all that could ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinguiſh her moſt innocent flames, faſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ings, hair ſhifts, and all other rigorous uſage were put in practice, and the change of a more reaſonable Directour than her former, brought not the leaſt Diminution to her folly. She was four whole years in this condition, and would have remained ſo in it ſtill, had not a fit of Devotion forced her out of it. Amongſt the Counſels ſhe had received from her ancient Directour, ſhe practiſed one with an unequall'd regularity; which was, to have recourſe to a Picture of St. <hi>Alexis,</hi> the Mirrour of Chaſtity, which was in her Oratory, and to proſtrate her ſelf there,, when ſhe ſaw her ſelf preſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed by temptations, or that ſhe felt in her thoſe movements which ſhe accuſed her ſelf ſo often of. Thus one day that ſhe found her ſelf more moved than uſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>al, and that her nature attacked her brisker than was cuſtomary, ſhe had re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>courſe to her Saint; repreſented to him with tears in her eyes, her face upon the floor, and her heart lifted up towards Heaven, the extreame danger ſhe found her ſelf in; related to him with a won<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derful candour and ſimplicity, to how little purpoſe ſhe had defended her ſelf,
<pb n="142" facs="tcp:171144:78"/>and uſed all her efforts to repreſs the violent tranſports ſhe was ſeized with.</p>
               <p>She accompanyed her prayers with Penance and Diſcipline, which ſhe inflicted in the preſence of this welbeloved Pilgrim. But as they tell of him that he was not in the leaſt toucht with the Beauty of his Wife on the firſt Night of his Wedding, but abandoned her on the Contrary, the beautiful Body of this innocent Creature expoſed naked before him, made no im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſſion upon his Spirit, and the laſhes ſhe ſo briskly ſwinged her ſelf with did not move him in any wiſe to compaſſion. Af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter having clawed her ſelf off in this man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner, ſhe recommended her ſelf anew to this good <hi>Roman,</hi> and withdrew as one victo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rious, to go paſs her time in Peace in leſs fatiguing exerciſes.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Agn.</speaker>
               <p>Good God! What a busſle and hurry does Superſtition make in the ſoul when it has once got poſſeſſion of it!</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Ang.</speaker>
               <p>
                  <hi>Doſithea</hi> was hardly got out of her Room, than that ſhe found her bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy all of a ſire, and her mind inclined to the purſuit of a pleaſure which ſhe was not yet acquainted with. An extraordi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nary tickling animated all her ſences, and her imagination filling it ſelf with a a thouſand laſcivious Ideas left this
<pb n="143" facs="tcp:171144:78"/>Poor Religious half vanquiſhed. In this pittious condition ſhe returned to her Interceſſour, redoubled her prayers, and conjured him by all that Devotion can have moſt ſenſible to grant her the gift of Continency; her ſervency did not ſtop there, ſhe took Inſtruments of pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nance in hand, and made uſe of 'em for a quarter of an hour together, with the maddeſt and moſt indiſcreet zeale ima<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ginable.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Agn.</speaker>
               <p>Well but this gave her ſome eaſe, did it not?</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Ang.</speaker>
               <p>Alas! Far from that, ſhe retired from her Oratory more and more tranſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ported with Love than before. The Bell rung to <hi>Veſpers</hi> much ado had ſhe to aſſiſt at 'em all the while. Sparkes of fire flew out at her eyes, and without knowing what ſhe fuffered, I admired her inſtability, and at her being in ſo continual a motion.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Agn.</speaker>
               <p>But from whence proceeded this?</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Ang.</speaker>
               <p>This was occaſioned by the ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tream heat ſhe felt over all her Body, and eſpecially in thoſe parts where ſhe had diſciplined her ſelf; for you muſt know theſe ſorts of exerciſes were ſo far from extinguiſhing the flames wherewith ſhe was conſumed, that on the contrary they
<pb n="144" facs="tcp:171144:79"/>had more and more augmented them, and had reduced that poor creature into ſuch a condition, as that ſhe was hardly any longer able to bear with it. This is eaſy to conceive, foraſmuch as the laſhes ſhe had clawed her backſide with, had ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cited heat in all the Neighbourhood, had brought thither the pureſt and moſt ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tile ſpirits of the blood, which to find an Iſſue conformable to their nature all of fire, did prick ſo notably the parts where they were aſſembled, as if it were to make a paſſage.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Agn.</speaker>
               <p>Did the conflict laſt long?</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Ang.</speaker>
               <p>It began and ended in a day; for as ſoon as Veſpers were over, <hi>Doſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thea,</hi> as if ſhe could not directly have addreſſed her ſelf to God, went to pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrate her ſelf again before her Oratory, Prayed, Wept, Groaned, but all to no purpoſe. She found her ſelf more preſſed than ever, and to inſult a-new this ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtinate Nature, ſhe took her whip in hand, and lifting up her Peticoats and ſmock to her Navel, and tying them up with a girdle, ſhe outraged her buttocks with extraordinary violence, and that part which put her to ſo much pain be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing all uncovered. This raging having laſted for ſome time, her ſtrength fail'd
<pb n="145" facs="tcp:171144:79"/>her for that cruel exerciſe, nay <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 span">
                     <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                  </gap> not enough left to untie her clothes, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 span">
                     <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                  </gap> expoſed her half naked, ſhe leane <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 span">
                     <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                  </gap> her head upon the Bed, and <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 span">
                     <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                  </gap> reflection upon the Condition of <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 span">
                     <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                  </gap> kind which ſhe called Unhappy, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 span">
                     <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                  </gap> they were born with motions <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 span">
                     <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                  </gap> condemned, tho' it was almoſt in <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 span">
                     <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                  </gap> ble to bridle them. She fell into <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 span">
                     <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                  </gap> of a trance, but it was an amou<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap> 
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 span">
                     <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                  </gap> trance cauſed by the fury of the paſſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="3 letters">
                     <desc>•••</desc>
                  </gap> and which made that poor young <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 span">
                     <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                  </gap> enjoy ſuch a delight as raviſh'd he <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 span">
                     <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                  </gap> the very Heavens. In that moment <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 span">
                     <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                  </gap> ture uniting all its forces, and Virgi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="3 letters">
                     <desc>•••</desc>
                  </gap> which tell then had been a Captive, d<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="3 letters">
                     <desc>•••</desc>
                  </gap>vered it ſelf without any help with an<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap> petuoſity, in leaving there the Keeper <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 span">
                     <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                  </gap> tended upon the floor for an evid<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="3 letters">
                     <desc>•••</desc>
                  </gap> token of her Defeat.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Agn.</speaker>
               <p>O Lord! Oh Lord! I wiſh I <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 span">
                     <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                  </gap> been by!</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Ang.</speaker>
               <p>Alas! What pleaſure could <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 span">
                     <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                  </gap> have been to thee? Thou wouldſt <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 span">
                     <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                  </gap> ſeen that innocent Creature ſighing <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 span">
                     <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                  </gap> panting, which ſhe knew not the cauſe <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 span">
                     <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                  </gap> Thou wouldeſt have ſeen her in an <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="3 letters">
                     <desc>•••</desc>
                  </gap>tacy, her eyes half dying without Viv<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap> city or Vigour, yeilding to the Laws <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> meer Nature, &amp; loſe maugre all her <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <pb n="146" facs="tcp:171144:80"/>that Treaſure, the keeping whereof had put her to ſo much pain.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Agn.</speaker>
               <p>Well this is what I ſhould have taken delight in, to view her thus all naked, and to obſerve curiouſly all the tranſports, that Love would have cauſed in her at the moment ſhe was overcome.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Ang.</speaker>
               <p>As ſoon as <hi>Doſithea</hi> was recove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red from this Rapture, her mind which was before clouded and buried in thick darkneſs, found it ſelf unvailed at the very inſtant of all its obſcurity: Her eyes were opened, and reflecting upon what ſhe had done, and upon the little virtue of her Saint, whom ſhe had ſo much invoked, ſhe knew ſhe had been in an errour, and thus raiſed her ſelf by her own ſtrength through a ſurprizing <hi>Metamorphoſis,</hi> above all things which ſhe durſt not before look upon, and had nothing but a contempt for what before ſhe had the greateſt Veneration.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Agn.</speaker>
               <p>That is to ſay, that of Scrupu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lous, ſhe became Indevout, and Irreli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gious, and that ſhe made no more Offe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rings to all the little Saints ſhe adored before.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Ang.</speaker>
               <p>Thou takeſt things in a wrong ſence; we may rid our ſelves of Super<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtition without falling into Impiety;
<pb n="147" facs="tcp:171144:80"/>which was what <hi>Doſithea</hi> did; ſhe had learnt by experience, that it was to the Soveraign Phyſitian, that recourſe is to be had to in one's weakneſſes and fail<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ings, that temptations were not in the power of the faithful, and that in the moſt ſubmiſſive Soul, there often aroſe involuntary thoughts and motions, which however could not occaſion any fault or imperfection. Thou ſeeſt how that I told thee nothing but what is true, when I urg'd that it was Devotion that freed her from her ſcruples.</p>
               <p>Almoſt the ſame thing happened to an <hi>Italian</hi> Nun, Who after having pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrated her ſelf very often before the figure of a Child newly born, which ſhe called her little <hi>Jeſus,</hi> and had conju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red it ſeveral times to grant her the ſame thing by tender words which ſhe uttered with an extraordinary affecti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on. <hi>Dolce Signore Mio Gjeſu, fatte mi la gratia,</hi> ſeeing that all her prayers were without effect, ſhe fancied that the In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fancy of him ſhe invoked, was the cauſe thereof, and that ſhe ſhould find better redreſs in addreſſing her ſelf to the Image of the eternal Father, which repreſen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted him in a more advanced age: She went thereupon again to her little Lord,
<pb n="148" facs="tcp:171144:81"/>whom ſhe upbraided with his little ver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tue, proteſting that ſhe would never a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>muſe her ſelf with him, nor any little Child of his ſort; and left him in that manner applying to him theſe words of the Proverb. <hi>Chi S'impaccia con Fanciulli, con Fanciulli ſi ritrova.</hi> Do but reflect a little how far ſuperſtition does ſometimes go, &amp; to what an extremity of folly ignorance does ſometimes lead us.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Agn.</speaker>
               <p>The truth is that theſe examples are a ſenſible proof of what you now ſay, and that the ſimplicity of this Nun is unparellel'd: The <hi>Italian</hi> Women however doe not paſs for fools, they are ſaid to have an infinite deal of Wit, and that few things are capable of puz<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling them, and eſcaping their under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtanding.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Ang.</speaker>
               <p>That is true, generally ſpeak<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, but there are ever ſome who are not ſo ſharp, and ſo quick witted as the others. Beſides, it is not alwaies a ſign of ſtupidity to have doubts and ſcruples, for you muſt know, my Dear <hi>Agnes,</hi> that (unleſs it be things of Religion) there is nothing certain or ſure in this World, there is no ſide but may be maintained, we have commonly only falſe and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fuſed
<pb n="149" facs="tcp:171144:81"/>Notions of thoſe things, which we think we know moſt perfectly. Truth is yet more unknown, and all the pain<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> and artifices of men, who apply them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves to the ſearch of it, have not yet been able to render it ſenſible to us, tho they have often fancied they had found it out.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Agn.</speaker>
               <p>But how muſt we then manage our mind in ſo univerſal an Ignorance?</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Ang.</speaker>
               <p>You muſt my Child, to prevent the being miſtaken and abuſed, Conſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der things from their Riſe, view them in their pure naturals, and afterwards judge of them conformably to what we ſee thereof. You muſt above all avoid ſuffering your Reaſon to be prepoſſeſſed and prejudiced, neither muſt ye ſuffer it to be beſieged by the ſentiments of others, which commonly are only Opi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nions. And you muſt be cautious, how you ſuffer your ſelf to be taken by the eyes, and by the ears, that is to ſay, by a thouſand exteriour things, which are often made uſe of for the ſeducing our ſences, but ſtill preſerve our mind free and diſengaged, from the ſilly movings, and childiſh Maximes, with which the Vulgar is infatuated, who like Brute ani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mals run after all that is <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <pb n="150" facs="tcp:171144:82"/>'em, provided it be gilded with ſome fine appearance.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Agn.</speaker>
               <p>I underſtand all this well enough, and I fancy too that thy Argument might be puſhed on much farther, and comprehend therein many things which thou exempteſt from it. I muſt own there is a great deal of pleaſure in hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring thy diſcourſe, and though thou were't not ſo young, and ſo lovely as thou really art, thy Witt alone would render thee amiable. Priddee buſs me once.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Ang.</speaker>
               <p>With all my heart, My Dear Creature, I am overjoyed with pleaſing thee in any thing, and with having found in thee ſo much diſpoſition to receive the inſtructions which thou wanteſt. When our minds are cleared of thoſe clouds of Darkneſs, and freed from all manner of diſquiet, there is not a mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment in our whole lives, but that affords us ſome pleaſures, and which may procure to us recreation from the very torments and ſcruples of others. But let us lay aſide all this morality, wherein I have inſenſibly engaged my ſelf. Kiſs me my little Mignion, I love thee more than my own life.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <pb n="151" facs="tcp:171144:82"/>
               <speaker>Agn.</speaker>
               <p>Well, are you ſatisfied? thou little thinkeſt that People my ſee us here.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Ang.</speaker>
               <p>And what reaſon have we to fear? Let us go into that <hi>Arbour</hi> and there no body can ſee us. But <hi>I</hi> am not yet ſatisfied, thy kiſſes have nothing that's common, give me one after the <hi>Florentine</hi> way?</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Agn.</speaker>
               <p>I believe thou art mad? Does the World kiſs after the ſame manner? What doſt thou mean by kiſſing after the <hi>Florentime</hi> way?</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Ang.</speaker>
               <p>Come and Ile teach it thee.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Agn.</speaker>
               <p>Oh! Lord thou ſets me all of a Fire! Ah what a Laſcivious way haſt thou with thee! Prethee ſtand off; Ah how thou huggeſt me, thou devoureſt me!</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Ang.</speaker>
               <p>I muſt pay and reward my ſelf for the Leſſons that I give thee. Now this is the way that perſons uſe in kiſſing, who really Love one another, by A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mourouſly Lanching the tongue between the Lips of the Object one Adores; for my part I find nothing more ſweet, and more delicious, when we acquit our ſelves of it in due manner, and I never practice it without being Raviſht into an Extaſy, and without feeling through all my Body an extraordinary Titilation, and
<pb n="152" facs="tcp:171144:83"/>a certain I know not what, that I can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not expreſs to thee, than by telling thee, that it is a ſecret Pleaſure which ſpreads it ſelf Univerſally into all the moſt ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cret parts of my ſelf, which penetrates into the very bottom of my Heart, and which I have right to term, <hi>An Abridg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of Soveraign Voluptuouſneſs.</hi> But what not a word; what ſence doth it raiſe in thee?</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Agn.</speaker>
               <p>Did I not tell it thee ſuffici<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ently, when <hi>I</hi> let thee know that thou putteſt me all in a flame; but whence comes it that thou calleſt theſe ſort of kiſſes a <hi>kiſs after the Florentine mode?</hi>
               </p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Ang.</speaker>
               <p>The reaſon is, that amongſt all the <hi>Italians,</hi> the Ladyes of <hi>Florence</hi> paſs for the moſt Amourous, and do gene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rally Practiſe this kiſs after the man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner thou haſt received it from me. They take a ſingular delight therein, and ſay they do it in imitation of the <hi>Dove,</hi> which is an innocent Bird; and that they find therein <hi>I</hi> know not what that's Laſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>civious and Poignant, which they do not find and taſt in others. <hi>I</hi> am amaz'd that the <hi>Abbot</hi> and the <hi>Mendicant</hi> did not teach thee this during my retreat? for they have travelled <hi>Italy,</hi> and in all probability they have rendered them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves
<pb n="153" facs="tcp:171144:83"/>knowing in all the moſt ſecret practices of Love, which are peculiar to thoſe of the Country.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Agn.</speaker>
               <p>Truly my mind was employed in ſomething elſe, than theſe ſimple tri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fles when they came to ſee me, for me to remember 'em at preſent. <hi>I</hi> know very well, that there is no ſort of Careſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes and Follies, but what their Amo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rous fury bethought it ſelf of; but in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deed the Pleaſure <hi>I</hi> took therein was ſo Great, and the Raviſhment thoſe Tran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſports cauſed in me ſo Exceſſive, that <hi>I</hi> had not ſufficient freedom of Judge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment left to reflect thereon.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Ang.</speaker>
               <p>The Truth is, that the ſweet moments, wherein we enjoy that vo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>luptuouſneſs, doe ſo poſſeſs us, that we are not capable of withdrawing our ſelves by any application of our memo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry, nor to make an <hi>Agenda</hi> at that inſtant of all that paſſes within our ſelves. Yet <hi>I</hi> do not doubt but the <hi>Abbot</hi> and the <hi>Mendicant</hi> have extended their Galan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>try ſo far; for beſides thy having a Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vine mouth, they are perfectly infor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med of all the ſofteſt and moſt Engage<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing arts and ways of thoſe who know Paſſionately how to Love.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Agn.</speaker>
               <p>Alas! They know but too much
<pb n="154" facs="tcp:171144:84"/>of thoſe matters, for perſons conſecra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted to the Altars and devoted to Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinency.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Ang.</speaker>
               <p>This is pleaſant in you indeed, and thoſe who know thee not would think that thou ſpeakeſt ſeriouſly. But ſhall <hi>I</hi> tell thee my thought? <hi>I</hi> fancy that they cannot know too much, but that they might practiſe leſs? For cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain it is; that having the direction of Souls, they ought to have a perfect knowledg of Good as well as Evil, for the making a juſt diſtinction, and for exhorting with the more Vehemence, to the Love and purſuit of the one, and Preaching to us with the like zeal the a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>voiding and the averſion of the other. But they do nothing leſs than this, and the ill Books they draw their lights from, Corrupt their VVills as well as Enlighten their Underſtandings?</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Agn.</speaker>
               <p>
                  <hi>I</hi> fancy thou miſtakeſt and a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>buſeſt the terms, and that thou doſt not call to mind, that amongſt the Learned there is no Books that of its nature bears the Title of forbidden, and that the uſe alone we make thereof, gives it the quality of good, bad, or indiffe, rent.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Agn.</speaker>
               <p>Good God! Thy talking
<pb n="155" facs="tcp:171144:84"/>at this rate, makes me think thou ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veſt, and thou muſt agree with me, there are certain Books all whoſe parts are bad, and whoſe inſtructions are eſſenti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ally oppoſite to good Morality and the practice of Vertue. What canſt thou ſay of the <hi>School of <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>enus,</hi> and of that <hi>Infamous Phyloſophy,</hi> that has nothing but what's flat and inſipid, and all whoſe poor and ſilly Reaſonings can on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly perſwade low and vulgar Spirits, or only touch thoſe who are leaſt cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rupted, or who of themſelves ſuffer themſelves to be led away to all man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner of weakneſſes.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Agn.</speaker>
               <p>I own that that Book may be placed in the ranks of things uſeleſs, nay of thoſe that are forbidden; I wiſh I could recover again the time that I employed in reading it, and there was nothing in it that pleas'd me, nor but what I condemn'd. The <hi>Abbot</hi> who ſhew'd it me, gave me another which is almoſt upon the ſame matter, but which treats it and manages it with much more Wit and Ingenuity.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Ang.</speaker>
               <p>I know what Book thou mean<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eſt; it's as bad (as to manners) as the former, and though the purity of its Stile, and its eaſy Eloquence have
<pb n="156" facs="tcp:171144:85"/>ſomething agreable, this does not hin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der it from being infinitely dangerous, ſince the Flame and the briskneſs which ſparkle there in many places, do only ſerve to make people ſwallow with the better guſt the venom wherewith it is filled, and inſinuate it inſenſibly into the hearts of thoſe that are the leaſt ſuſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceptible; its Title is, <hi>The Academy of Ladyes: Or the Seven Satyrical Dialogues of Aloiſia.</hi> I have had it for above this <hi>Week</hi> in my hands, and he from whom <hi>I</hi> received it, explained to me the moſt difficult paſſages, and gave me a per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fect underſtanding of all it has myſte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rious. Eſpecially he interpreted to me theſe words, which are in the Seventh Dialogue, <hi>Amori, vera Lux,</hi> and diſco<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vered to me the anagramatical ſence which they concealed, under the ſimple appearance of the inſcription of a Me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dal. <hi>I</hi> fancy it was of this Book, that thou hadſt a deſign to ſpeak?</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Agn.</speaker>
               <p>Right, it was ſo. Lord, Lord, how ingenious it is in inventing new Pleaſures for a ſatiated and diſguſted mind! With what Points and with what Spurs does it revive that Luſt that is the moſt lulled aſleep, the moſt languiſhing, nay and that which is no
<pb n="157" facs="tcp:171144:85"/>longer able! What extravagant A<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="3 letters">
                     <desc>•••</desc>
                  </gap> tites! What ſtrange Objects! VV<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap> unknown Meats does it Offer! B<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap> perceive <hi>I</hi> am not yet ſo knowing <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> it as thou art.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Ang.</speaker>
               <p>Alas! my poor Child, the kn<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledg thou aſpireſt to, cannot but <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> prejudicial to thee? The Pleaſures <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> propoſe to our ſelves, ought to be bo<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded by the <hi>Laws,</hi> by Nature, and by P<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dence, and all the Maximes which t<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>t Book is capable of inſtructing thee w<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="3 letters">
                     <desc>•••</desc>
                  </gap> almoſt equally deviate from thoſe th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>e things. Take my word, all Extremities <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> dangerous; and there is a certain M<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="3 letters">
                     <desc>•••</desc>
                  </gap> way, which we cannot vary from with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out falling into the Precipice. <hi>I<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap> us Love,</hi> that is not prohibited; <hi>Seek <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>
                     <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter Pleaſure,</hi> as long as it is Lawful; b<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap> let us ſhun and avoid, what can only i<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpire Debauchery, and let us not ſuff<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap> our ſelves to be perſwaded by an El<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quence which only flatters us to our Ru<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ine, and which only expreſſes it ſelf well to hurry us the more eaſily to miſchief.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Agn.</speaker>
               <p>Goodly, Goodly, VVith your fine Morals forſooth! <hi>I</hi> find you know how to Gild the Pill when you pleaſe! Not but that <hi>I</hi> yeild to your Reaſons, and blame all thoſe things which thou con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>demneſt,
<pb n="158" facs="tcp:171144:86"/>but <hi>I</hi> cannot forbear laughing to ſee thee Preach Reformation with ſo much heat, and that <hi>I</hi> hear thee ſpeaking to the dumb, and to the blind: ſuch as are our Siſters, who will receive no rules, but ſuch as they propoſe to themſelves.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Ang.</speaker>
               <p>You are in the right; and <hi>I</hi> own it is time ill beſtowed, to labour the ſup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſſing of Vice, and the excelling of Virtue, in the Corruption of the Age we live in; the Diſeaſe is too great, end the Contagion too Univerſal to be reme<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dyed by plain VVords, and to be cu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red by a Potion and Preparation that can only act upon the mind. This is not my deſign, in the leaſt, but <hi>I</hi> was on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly very willing to let thee know, that <hi>I</hi> do not approve of the Libertiniſme of thoſe Perſons, who never enjoy perfect Pleaſures, unleſs they go ſeek them in the leſſons of a Corrupted imagination, beyond the moſt inviolable bounds of Nature, and even into the moſt diſſolute Licentiouſneſs of paſs'd Fables.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>I</hi> am no enemy to Sports, and De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lights, nor am <hi>I</hi> wedded to that trouble<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſome Vertue which our Age is not ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pable of. <hi>I</hi> know the moſt Noble ſoul cannot be Miſtreſs of its paſſions, nor purged from other humane infirmities
<pb n="159" facs="tcp:171144:86"/>as long as it is wedded to our Body.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Agn.</speaker>
               <p>Ah <hi>I</hi> am pleas'd with this re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turn! and this reaſonable indulgence may be perhaps allowed of. For what hurt can there be found in pleaſure when it is well regulated? Something of neceſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſity muſt be allowed to the temperament of the Body, and comply with the weak<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs of our minds, ſince we receive them ſo as Nature gave us them, and that it lies not in our Power to pick call and chuſe 'em. We are not reſponſible for the freaks, fancies, propenſities and in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clyations which it give us; if they are faults, 'tis it that is culpable and ought to be blamed. And men cannot be up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>braided with the vices that are born with them, or which only proceed from their Birth.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Ang.</speaker>
               <p>Thou ſpeakeſt reaſon, thou Dar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling of my Heart, and <hi>I</hi> cannot expreſs to thee the joy <hi>I</hi> feel, when that thy VVords make me ſee the Progreſs that thou haſt made by my inſtructions. But let us no longer puzzle and weary our Brains, after the ſearch and ripping up of other Peoples Crimes, let us bear with what we cannot reform, let us not touch nor glance upon Evils, that would undoubtedly diſcover the inſufficiency of
<pb n="160" facs="tcp:171144:87"/>our remedies. Let us live for our ſelves, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> without making our ſelves ſick with <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 span">
                     <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                  </gap> infirmities, let us Eſtabliſh in our <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 span">
                     <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                  </gap> that Spiritual Peace and Tran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="5 letters">
                     <desc>•••••</desc>
                  </gap>y, which is the Principle of the joy <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 span">
                     <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                  </gap> Beginning of the happyneſs which <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 span">
                     <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                  </gap> reaſonably deſire.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Agn.</speaker>
               <p>For my part I am already in <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> peaceable enjoyment of the repoſe, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 span">
                     <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                  </gap> the quiet of Spirit, to which I <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> ſay <hi>I</hi> could only attain to by thy <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 span">
                     <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                  </gap>. Theſe are Obligations which <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 span">
                     <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                  </gap> never ſufficiently acknowledge; <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 span">
                     <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                  </gap> new my Gratitude to that degree <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 span">
                     <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                  </gap> lay in my power, ſince for all <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 span">
                     <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                  </gap> thou haſt taken to free me out <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 span">
                     <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                  </gap> Error <hi>I</hi> was in, thou muſt content <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 span">
                     <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                  </gap> with the Affection <hi>I</hi> have ſworn <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 span">
                     <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                  </gap>, and it muſt ſerve thee inſtead of <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 span">
                     <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                  </gap> reward.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Ang.</speaker>
               <p>Alas! My dear Child, what <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 span">
                     <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                  </gap> thou offer me more to my Satis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>faction? <hi>I</hi> prefer thy Careſſes before all th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap> Treaſures in the VVorld; one ſole K<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="4 letters">
                     <desc>••••</desc>
                  </gap> thine Charms me, and puts me in<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap> 
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="3 letters">
                     <desc>•••</desc>
                  </gap>pture. But ſee, yonder is ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>B<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="4 letters">
                     <desc>••••</desc>
                  </gap> coming, let us part to hinder al<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap> 
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>icion they might have of our <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 span">
                     <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                  </gap> and diſcourſe. Buſs me, my <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 span">
                     <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                  </gap> 
                  <hi>Dove.</hi>
               </p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <pb n="161" facs="tcp:171144:87"/>
               <speaker>Agn.</speaker>
               <p>
                  <hi>I</hi> will ſo, and it shall be a ſuck<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing Kiſs, <hi>I</hi> mean after the mode of <hi>Flo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rence.</hi>
               </p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Ang.</speaker>
               <p>Ah thou Ravisheſt me with De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>light! I am in a Tranſport! Ah 'tis too much for me to bear! Thou cauſeſt in me a <hi>Thouſand</hi> Pleaſures.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Agn.</speaker>
               <p>Well, this is ſufficient for the pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent. Farewell <hi>Angelica,</hi> 'tis Siſter <hi>Cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nelia,</hi> ſhe's a coming.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Ang.</speaker>
               <p>I ſee her, 'tis without doubt to bring me ſome meſſage from my Lady <hi>Abbeſs.</hi> Adieu <hi>Agnes,</hi> Adieu my <hi>Heart,</hi> my <hi>Souls-Delight,</hi> my <hi>Love.</hi>
               </p>
            </sp>
            <trailer>THE END.</trailer>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
